Well, good afternoon and welcome to the
July 6th meeting of the public services
committee. Um this afternoon, if you
will, if you are here with us in person,
if you will make sure that your um cell
phones are silenced, um that would be
helpful. And um if you are going to make
public comment, if you will uh when you
come to the podium, please make sure
that you um state your name for the
record. Um if you are going to
participate virtually today online, um
please use the raise hand function and
uh when uh Jennifer lets you know that
you're able to speak, you'll be able to
make public comment.
Um with that said, um we are only going
to be discussing things on the agenda
today. Um, we have a full agenda. So,
um, with that, Jennifer, would you read
the first item? Number nine, ordinance
third reading, annexing to the city of
Cheyenne, Wyoming, land located south of
Charles Street, east of Win Andy Avenue
and west of McKinley Avenue.
Okay. Staff report. Morgan
Morgan Dennis, Planning and Development.
Um, this is an annexation for 2.69
acres. Um, this was approved on second
reading and nothing else has changed and
I will stand for questions.
Okay. Is there any questions from the
committee?
Was there any public did anyone reach
out to you Morgan since the
>> Madam Chair to you? No, there has been
no public comment.
>> Thank you. Okay, we'll go out for public
comment. Any public comment?
Okay, seeing none or hearing none, I
would uh entertain a motion.
>> So move.
>> Okay, we have a motion from Councilman
Leborn.
>> Second.
>> A second from Councilman Renie. Any
discussion?
Hearing none. All in favor say I.
Opposed.
Okay. This item will move forward with a
recommendation to approve at the next
meeting of the council. Next item,
number 10, ordinance, third reading,
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne, establishing the
zoning classification of AR,
agricultural residential for land annex
to the city of Cheyenne, located south
of Charles Street, east of Winandandy
Avenue, and west of McKinley Avenue.
Hey, staff report, please.
>> Morgan Dennis, planning and development.
Um, this is the associated assigned
zoning for the annexation. Um there this
was approved on second reading. There
has been no public comment and I stand
for questions.
Are there any questions from the
committee?
Okay, we'll go out for public comment.
I don't see any public comment.
Okay. Okay. Um so, uh I would entertain
a motion.
Um, Madam Chairwoman, I move to approve
on third and final reading.
>> We have a motion from Dr. Emmens,
>> second
>> and a second from Dr. Renie. Any
discussion?
>> All those in favor say I.
>> I.
>> Opposed? This item will move forward
with our recommendation to approve at
the next meeting of the council. Next
item, please. Number 11, ordinance,
third reading, annexing to the city of
Cheyenne, Wyoming, land northwest of the
intersection of Clear Creek Parkway and
Ganet Peak Drive.
Okay. Staff report, please.
>> Madam Chair, members of the committee,
Connor Way Planning and Development
Department. Uh the annexation before you
is out in Swan Ranch. Um this was
approved on second reading. There's been
no further public comment that I've had
with anybody on this project. Um, and I
have no new information, so I'm
available for any questions.
>> Thank you. Any questions from committee?
Okay, we'll go out for public comment.
Any public comment?
>> Hearing none. Um, or seeing none, uh, I
would entertain a motion.
>> Madam Chairwoman, I approve move to
approve on third and final reading.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion from Dr. Emmens and a
second from Dr. Renie. Um any
discussion?
All in favor say I.
>> I.
>> Opposed. This item will move forward
with recommendation to approve at the
next meeting of the council. Next item,
please. Number 12, ordinance, third
reading, amending the official zoning
map of the city of Cheyenne,
establishing the zoning classification
of LI light industrial for land annex to
the located northwest of the
intersection of Clear Creek Parkway and
Ganet Peak Drive.
>> Okay. Staff report please.
>> Madam chair, members of the committee,
Conor White Planning and Development
Department uh with any annexation, we
have the assigned zoning. This proposes
assigning the LI zone to this parcel
upon annexation. There's been no new
information. Uh no additional public
comments that I've had on this project.
I am available for any questions.
>> Is there any questions from committee?
Okay. Any public comment?
Okay. Hearing none or seeing none, I
would entertain a motion.
>> Madam Chairwoman, I'd move to approve on
third reading.
>> Second. We have a motion from Dr. Renie,
a second from Dr. Emmens to approve. Um,
any discussion?
>> All in favor say I.
>> I.
>> Opposed. This item will move forward
with recommendation to approve at the
next meeting of the council. Next item,
please. Number 13, ordinance, third
reading, amending the official zoning
map of the city of Cheyenne, changing
the zoning classification for land
located north and south of West Wall
Road and west of Interstate 25 from LI
Light Industrial CB Community Business
and PUBG Planned Unit development to BP
Business Park. Staff report please.
>> Chair, members of committee, Conor
Planning and Development Department. the
zone change before you, it goes along
with the annexation, the assigned
zoning, so similar parcels involved does
have additional parcels uh involved to
reach the 320 acres for the BP zone. Uh
this does take several zone districts
out in this uh industrial area and
combines them just into the BP zone. Um
there's been no new public comment. I
have no new information. This was
approved on second reading and I'm
available for any questions. Any
questions from committee?
Okay, we'll go out for public comment.
>> Okay. Hearing or seeing none, I would
entertain a motion.
>> Madam Chairwoman, I move to approve on
third and final reading.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion from Dr. Emmens with a
second from Dr. Renie to approve. Any
discussion?
All those in favor say I. All those
opposed. This item will move forward
with a recommendation to approve at the
next meeting of the council. Next item,
please. Number 14, Ordinance, third
reading. Annexing to the city of
Cheyenne, Wyoming, land east of South
Kley Highway and south of the Sweetg
Grass subdivision.
Okay. Staff report.
>> Madam chair, members of committee,
underway planning and development.
Again, uh the annexation before you is
for land south of Sprass. Um
it was approved on second reading. I've
had no new public comments related to
this item. Um and with that, I'm stand
for any questions.
>> Thank you. Any questions from committee?
>> Okay. Any public comment?
Um, chairwoman, Dr. Aldrich, council
members, Bradi,
agent for the applicant and owners on
this. I just wanted to reiterate that uh
we believe that this meets the state
statute criteria for annexation which
has been outlined in state statutes and
reviewed by the city staff. And uh we
believe the BP zoning is uh meets the
criteria for the BP zoning for item 13
or 15. Um be happy to be here. We can
get back up if there's questions as we
move forward, but just wanted to let you
know we're here to answer any questions
you have.
>> Thank you, Mr.
>> Thank you.
>> Good afternoon.
>> Good afternoon, uh chair, members of the
public service committee. My name is
Rachel Irwing. I'm the land development
manager for Microsoft and for the record
our address is one Microsoft way Redmond
Washington. Um I appreciate the
opportunity to be here again with you
today to speak on the Highlands
annexation and resoning applications. Uh
we also appreciate the time that the
city staff, council and community
members have invested in reviewing,
discussing and providing feedback on
this project throughout the process so
far. Um I would like to briefly
reiterate a few points that are
important for the record and for public
understanding. Uh first, while full
buildout for a project of this scale
would develop over many years, planning
must begin well in advance, uh
entitlement, infrastructure planning,
engineering, utility coordination,
environmental review, traffic
evaluation, and permitting are all
longlead efforts. Uh the annexation
resoning requests before you today
establish the framework for those
evaluations and decisions to occur
throughout the city's established
processes. Uh second, annexation and
zoning are important milestones, but
they are not the end of project review.
As planning advances, there will be
additional studies, agency reviews,
permitting requirements, infrastructure
planning, and agreements as appropriate.
Those processes are intended to further
evaluate potential impacts, identify
needed improvements, and help ensure
development occurs responsibly and in
coordination with community and
reviewing agencies. Third, Microsoft
recognizes the importance of
infrastructure investment and
understands that growth must be
supported by the facilities and services
necessary to serve it. We have a long
history of working with local
governments, utility providers, and
community partners to address
infrastructure needs associated with our
developments. As this project
progresses, we look forward to
continuing those discussions through
appropriate planning, engineering, and
review processes. Finally, we value the
partnership that we have built with the
city of Cheyenne and broader community.
We understand that there are questions
about the future of this site, and we
welcome those conversations. We also
recognize that the conversations about
growth often extend beyond the
infrastructure required to support a
specific development. Microsoft
understands the importance of investing
in our communities where we operate and
we anticipate making significant
investments in Cheyenne. We look forward
to continuing those conversations with
city leadership, community stakeholders,
and residents as planning progresses.
Thank you.
>> Thank you.
>> Good afternoon.
>> There we go. Good afternoon, chair and
members of the committee. My name is
Lucas Downey and I work on the Microsoft
community affairs team. I promise to
keep this brief. At this point, I think
some of us have spent enough time
together this summer and that we're
starting to recognize each other's
speaking patterns. As we've done
throughout the process, I want to simply
restate Microsoft's community first
commitments for the public record.
First, we'll pay our way to ensure our
data centers don't increase electricity
prices. Second, we'll minimize our water
use and replenish more water than we
use. Third, we'll create jobs for local
residents. Fourth, we'll add to the tax
base. and fifth will strengthen
communities through investments in
workforce training and local nonprofits.
Microsoft has been a part of the
Cheyenne community for more than 14
years and these commitments continue to
guide how we operate and invest here.
Thank you.
>> Thank you. Any other public comment?
>> Good afternoon, Councilman Wolf.
>> Madam Chairman, uh members of the
committee, nice to see you. Uh Larry
Wolf, uh Ward One, uh city councilman.
Um I come before you today to um make a
um further request that we slow this
process down a bit. Um and uh I've
prepared a um draft motion for you. It
um
does really one simple thing. Dr. any
it um
strikes the current section five in the
ordinance which is essentially the
enacting clause and um restates it with
a substitute and the substitute is two
sentences. It says that this ordinance
shall be in full force in effect on
December 31st 2026.
Second sentence is the purpose of the
delayed effective date is to allow the
mayor and the staff time to negotiate a
community benefit agreement with
Microsoft Inc.
This is the largest annexation the city
has ever done. It's the largest we
probably will ever do because of the way
blocks of land are being uh acquired uh
right now.
This is a monumental
undertaking that we should treat in such
a fashion with the respect that it
deserves.
And all this motion does and all I'm
asking and my co-sponsors, Councilman
Leburn and Moody, is to give you members
of the council and all of us a historic
opportunity to actually build
projects, build infrastructure that will
make a permanent
lasting improvement in the city of
Cheyenne and do that through a
partnership with Microsoft.
Yes, they are a good community member.
Yes, they contribute good jobs. They
have loyal employees.
They contribute to the community in ways
that are of interest to them.
What I'm saying is that we, the city of
Cheyenne, need to learn from the last
five years of nationwide development of
data centers where cities initially
welcome data centers with open arms, but
that has fundamentally changed.
We should consider this an opportunity
to work with Microsoft in a way that
benefits all of us. At this point, if
you just grant this annexation, there
are only two beneficiaries of it.
The Lumis family who's selling the land
and Microsoft.
That land is going to sit there
undeveloped
for at least a decade probably. Yes,
there's planning. Yes, the things that
big corporations do when they own big
chunks of land.
But we're going to get no additional
revenues from it. We're going to get no
buildings on it of any substantial size,
no sales tax. All the things that we
have been looking at and have helped
sustain this city.
We have needs in this city that
Microsoft and its employees who are
residents here and the ones who aren't
residents here take advantage of. I was
in the civic center on Thursday watching
1776. I think you were there, Madam
Chairman.
I saw the line of 40 women trying to go
to the bathroom at intermission.
That building would make a perfect
community project probably for all the
data centers in this community to
renovate that building. And that's just
one of many examples.
Storm water drainage with Mr. Cobb and
the city engineers office, the pump
house, the list goes on and on.
We can in fact use this time, the mayor
and the staff will take the opportunity
and if you'll give them the opportunity
to negotiate
agreements and remember that
governments change
and corporations change and promises
that they make to us today at this
podium
may be marketkedly different in the next
few years.
Also, I circulated to all of you a
analysis that our friends at AI did and
said, where has Microsoft actually
entered into agreements with communities
and they have done this in parts of the
country, significant agreements,
tens of millions of dollars, hundreds of
millions of dollars. So there's nothing
extraordinary about what we're asking
for today.
In fact, these kinds of agreements have
become the norm.
And we should take the opportunity now
to take the time to do this.
And if you go forward with this and our
final vote will be on Monday and we
annex this and we reszone it, you will
have lost the opportunity,
lost the ability to make Microsoft the
kind of significant partner that it can
and should be. So I would urge you and I
will urge you again on Monday to think
and act in the interests the long-term
interests of this city
think and act in a way that reflects how
can we make
how can we make Microsoft and the city
into the kind of partnership that will
in fact provide the kind of long-term
benefits and investment that this city
needs.
Thank you.
>> Thank you. Is there any other public
comment? And uh we have been remiss in
starting the three-minut timer, so we
will not use it on this item, but we
will uh start that with the next item.
So, yes.
>> Yes.
>> No, I would rather you ask him now so he
doesn't have to come back up. So, okay.
Go ahead, Dr.
>> Thank you, Madam Chair. Um, yeah, I have
a couple of questions. First of all,
I hear three purposes in this which I'm
trying to sort out in my brain. One is
to stop it. One is the size of the
annexation as a concern and the third is
the community benefit agreement. So,
which problem are we trying to solve
with this?
>> Madam Chairman, for you? Well,
I'm only trying to solve the problems I
think, council woman, that I can solve.
I'm not asking you to stop the
annexation.
This motion actually would grant the
annexation. It would just delay the
effective date for 6 months.
So
and and the reason to do that which I've
stated in the motion and which would
become part of the ordinance that would
be adopted next Monday if this motion
were to pass and amend the draft
ordinance is that annexation would be
granted. They would know that in fact
this property is going to become part of
the city, but we would have time to work
out these kinds of complex partnership
arrangements with Microsoft during that
time.
>> Then I have a followup. Sure.
>> Um through you. So, do you believe that
it's that the mayor doesn't have the
capacity to develop an agreement with
Microsoft regarding going forward
without this amendment? Can he not do
that like he's done with some of the
other groups?
>> Um, madam chairman through you, uh,
chairwoman through you.
The mayor has the power.
What he needs is
the ability
to be in a position
of negotiating equality.
That's what I'm trying to create.
Because if we don't do it in this way,
if you grant the annexation,
grant the zoning change,
you've given away everything.
>> So follow up. What is stopping the
mayor? Why why can the mayor not do it
on his own?
>> Uh madam chairman, uh frankly,
councilwoman, I don't know. I mean, it
seems to me
completely in the mayor's interest,
in the city's interest to have done
this.
Pre-anexation agreements
are common place. I went to the law
library, something I haven't done for a
long time, and was reading McQuillin,
which is the Bible of municipal law.
And they have a whole section about
pre-anexation agreements. And the reason
you do it now, the reason you have to do
it now is because you have a level
negotiating field. The city has things
that they need. They have a partnership
they want to build. And Microsoft has
something they need, which is access to
our water and sewer, police, and fire,
and all the other aspects of being part
of this city.
And that's why this is so significant.
That's why this is so much more than the
mayor said the other night, which is
it's just changing the color on the map.
No, it's not. That is not the way you
should look at annexation. That's not
the way the statute looks at annexation.
I'm going to I'm preparing a a closing
argument that I'll deliver on Monday. If
we can't get this issue resolved between
now and then, we should take the time
that we have. They're not going to
develop this property for years. I mean,
the notion that there's some dire impact
about not granting the annexation
and and to their planning is absurd.
We have given them ample opportunity.
I've been to every single one of these
hearings, sat through all of them and
the planning commission
for them to say to us, oh, you know,
this might be two years, this might be
five years, this might be whenever it's
10 years away.
So what could 6 months
possibly make in the difference between
what they're doing? But it makes a huge
difference and what we're doing.
>> So uh through you madam chair. So just
for clarification there's nothing that
stops the mayor from pursuing an
agreement with Microsoft for community
betterment activities. Well, Madam
Chairman, through you. Um, well, but
it's the the difference is substantial,
Councilwoman.
The difference is
whether the mayor comes to the table
and looks across the table at Microsoft
and says,
"Here's the partnership we'd like to
build with you. Here are the things we
would like to help you with."
If the council has already given away
the thing that Microsoft
really wants,
which is the annexation
and the zoning, if we've already
conceded that, Microsoft
can and might
and may look at us and say, "That's
nice. We appreciate talking to you, but
we're already part of the city.
We're already here. You already gave us
that
power. And yes, it's a two-way street,
but only within certain limitations.
It's this decision, that's why this
decision, I've been saying this for a
month and a half, is so important and
why we ought to take the time to think
about how important it is and why the
mayor doesn't think that this is
actually a great opportunity that he
should uh take. I don't understand. I've
asked several times. I've gotten no
answer.
Dr. Winnie.
>> Thank you, Madam Chairwoman.
To um Councilman Wolf. So, my
understanding is this this amendment
does grant Microsoft their annexation
and does grant them their requested
zoning. It just postpones the effective
date till the end of the year. Is that
correct?
>> Um Madam Chairman, through you. Well, it
doesn't grant the zoning, Dr. Renie, it
just grants the annexation.
>> So it just grant But it does grant the
annexation. Correct.
>> Yes.
>> Okay. So if we're granting the
annexation and postponing just
postponing till the end of the year,
didn't we just give away our leverage?
>> Madam Chairman, through you
some which is actually this is why this
is not my preferred solution. My
preferred solution I brought to this
committee and to the council last
meeting which was to actually postpone
any decision on this for another 5
months. I think that actually is a
stronger negotiating position, but the
one I'm proposing to you today is
a compromise. It's less effective, I
think, from a legal standpoint, but it's
still effective. And that's why I would
encourage you to do it. But your point
is very well taken, Dr. Renie, that by
conceding the annexation, they they they
have the they have the certainty. Um, it
may in fact put us in a slightly weaker
position from a negotiating standpoint,
but it's still there. and the council
could come back in November and say
we're not there yet. The negotiation
isn't complete. We need more time and
extend that day.
>> Madam Chair, one more question. Um, so
to Councilman Wolf, that's if we work on
the hypothetical that this is that the
uh amendment is adopted.
And so the wording says it's to give the
mayor and staff time to negotiate
community benefit agreement.
Does the proponents of the amendment
have a minimum of what's acceptable in a
community benefit agreement? And would
they argue against that agreement if if
they determine that the mayor did not
negotiate? Well,
>> uh, Madam Chairman, through you. Um,
that's an excellent question, Dr. Renie,
and one I've given a lot of thought to.
Um, if you recall, my original motion
had a whole set of criteria in it. But
after listening to you, listening to my
fellow councilmen,
uh, and thinking about this, I've taken
all of that out.
This is a simple two Senates amendment.
I have drafted in a way to respect
the power of the executive,
the mayor's power to represent the city
in this and set no conditions, no
boundaries, no constraints around that.
What I would hope would happen is that
the mayor would communicate with us as
that process goes forward, that he would
take the time and to think about this.
Could we be in a position where uh
somebody on the council thought the
agreement was not enough?
We could also be in a position where we
thought it was too much. All that's
possible, but I've not tried to
anticipate any of that, nor tried to put
any limitations on what the mayor and
his staff might uh might decide was
appropriate.
>> Thank you, Madam Chairwoman.
>> U may I ask a question? Um, Councilman
Wolf, my question is in the wording of
this last sentence, it says, "The
purpose of the delayed effective deate
is to allow the mayor and staff time to
negotiate a community benefit agreement
with Microsoft, Inc." Uh, what that does
not mandate the mayor to do that. So,
the mayor could choose not to negotiate.
And then where are we?
>> Um, Madam Chairman, I I have worried
about that too and tried to to
anticipate that. And I think the answer
to that question is
that we're really have to rely on the
mayor and his staff to make the
judgments that are best for the city. Um
I I I actually thought here it's
something that I I've learned from you
um uh councilman and chairwoman u about
like putting in an interim report or
something. So, but even that might be
argued as intruding on on the mayor and
and his staff's uh ability to do this.
So, I didn't do that. You know, I'm open
to any of those changes. Um I added this
one sentence just to make it clear for
anybody in the public who's reading this
why we're doing this, what the basis uh
of it is. Um, but uh I uh and the mayor
could could clearly he could come to us
and say I either can't do it or I won't
do it or the things that we're already
doing are sufficient uh or all our needs
have been met. Whatever. I I I I don't
think we can anticipate all the things
that might happen. But this this this
does a couple really clear things. It
says okay take six months sit down with
Microsoft
figure out what it is and and this is
not just investment this is this is the
other part this is the part that was in
my original motion which is
we we live in a time in which things
that we thought we understood about
corporate behavior
can change in an instant or change in an
election.
And that's why we need to think about
all of these promises that Microsoft
make makes because they aren't
immutable.
They can come here and stand at the
podium and tell you we're going to do
this, we're going to do that.
Corporations change and can change
dramatically in totally different
directions.
things that they might promise us now
which are
taking going back to my environmental
law heritage best available control
technology could become best available
cheapest technology.
So we want to think about those things
as well. It's not just how we build this
relationship to help the city. It's to
think about the other kinds of promises
that may be made. For instance, and I
raised this uh in my discussion with uh
director Bloom, you know, I asked him,
"What if Microsoft 10 years from now
says, not only do we want to have these
data centers, but we also want to build
our own energy plant there, just like
Tallrass and Vantage are doing. And we
want you to supply water for that
because we're now part of the city and
we're entitled to it.
We need to think about what that
possibility might be. And if you recall
in my initial draft, I said
we would exclude the provision of water
for your power plant as part of our
obligations to provide water and sewer
to this project. Now, that may be
far-fetched. You could argue that uh
well, they're not going to do that.
they're going to buy their power from
Black Hills 10 years from now. Who
knows? So I I would ask you and this is
all part of thinking both broadly and
creatively
and none of it's directed to denigrate
Microsoft for whom I have an enormous
amount of respect. I mean that sort of
they they've been really important
partners with us, but that we as a city
when you're talking about these
long-term undertakings
need to be very thoughtful about it and
be very thoughtful about the commitments
that we the city are making to it.
>> Thank you, Dr. Emmens. Thank you, Miss
uh Madam Chair. One other question I had
that um I just remembered. So in the
document that you sent us regarding the
investments in other communities, it
seemed if I remember right, a lot of
those were things around water and
electricity and power which we already
have a commitment from Microsoft for
those things. Is that not correct?
Well, Madam Chairman, I I I I think your
reading of that, Councilwoman, is
exactly right. That's I think what a lot
of them are around. Um, but that's not
the universe of what you can talk with
them about. Uh and and yes, I mean in
some of those instances
um there have been some really
apparent deficits in the community's uh
infrastructure system and and Microsoft
and other companies do this too have
have agreed to invest in that. um we may
not need that because we have a very
robust uh system
and you can argue about what's happened
in the last 3 months but um so and and
so our needs will be different but that
doesn't make them any less important in
terms of actually addressing those and
arriving in agreement with Microsoft on
them.
>> Thank you. I I understand what you're
saying. I just wanted to be clear so
we're not comparing apples and
grapefruits.
>> Well, Madam Chairman, I um through you I
I I agree and I I think the point's very
well taken, Councilwoman, that um some
of these exist because just of that, but
that's that's nowhere near the extent of
the the issues you could you can talk
with them about.
>> Any other questions for Councilman Wolf?
>> Thank you. Thank you, Madam Chairman.
Thank you, members.
>> I think we have more public comment
here.
>> Yeah. Uh not until we go to the next
topic. I don't think it's fair to That's
okay. It's not your fault.
>> Good afternoon, uh public services
committee. My name is Marian Callas,
candidate for W one. Um, I I would like
to offer my support to
um
delaying the
you're delaying the um not the
annexation but the zoning seems like
effective date. Okay. Um well, I I would
like to reference um an article in
Brookings. Um they are an American think
tank. They've been around for over a
hundred years. They're nonpartisan and
their mission is to um provide economic
solutions, economic and social solutions
for policy makers. And they did a really
in-depth, pretty good article on data
centers and um how um communities can
small communities like ours can be
engaged in um mutually beneficial
partnership
um for continued prosperity.
And
some of this was a little bit dense, but
it did talk about um Microsoft and how
it does already have partnerships with
some communities in Wisconsin. Um and so
they're not new to this that you know I
I honestly think maybe they're just
waiting for us to to approach them with
something. Um they all in this article
they they spoke of like um it's it was
done for in oil and gas with like Alaska
and North Dakota and land endowments.
Like this isn't a new thing for
communities to be in partnership with
big industry to in to insulate
themselves from potential busts. Um and
so those payouts in Alaska and North
Dakota are still happening. Um
we are in very changeable conditions
with this new industry. I I did go to
the data center um meeting that you guys
had. It was very informative. There was
a question about reclamation
and um the answer that was given I
didn't think was very satisfactory. Um
it was well we've been doing this for 20
years and we haven't seen any any
decline. we don't think that this
industry will decline. Um, I don't think
that's a good argument. I mean, think of
it as a prenup. You know, we we really
love each other. We don't think this
marriage is going to end, but maybe we
should have something in place in case
it does. So, I just think that maybe
Cheyenne should be thinking like that,
too. In case there is something that
goes on within this industry that we
can't even foresee, we're not on the
hook for having to
perhaps do some cleanup.
um that could be something that could be
in the partnership.
So, those are just my thoughts. Um I'm
in support and thank you.
>> Thank you.
>> Good afternoon.
>> Good afternoon, madam chair and members
of the committee. Betsy Hail, CEO of
Cheyenne Leadeds. I reside at 17503 on a
loop Cheyenne. Um, since 2020, LEDs has
helped negotiate development agreements
and manage the construction of road and
bridge infrastructure that our community
so uh badly needs. And we are actively
working on three specific site projects
right now. Uh, we have managed over
hund00 million of infrastructure that
were requirements of development
agreements. And so I would discourage
the delay that's being proposed. It sort
of says that we're closed or we're
slowing down for business, but you're
also picking winners and losers because
you're only talking to one company.
You're not talking to all types of
industries, not just data centers, but
could be a meat processing plant, could
be a distribution center for Amazon,
could be an ammunition manufacturer or a
gun manufacturer. And so, I think we
really need to think about are we just
picking on this one project or are we
going to be thinking bigger about the
long-term future of our community? I do
think the idea of a community benefit
agreement is a good one. I spent the
last several months attending all of the
hearings and I actually took the time to
meet with Heather Madrid and
specifically sit down with her and ask
her about her comment and you might
remember her comment was we need to
think holistically and we need to think
regionally and we shouldn't just think
of these things as a projectby project
basis because we now are in a situation
where there could be three or four or
five projects coming out of the ground
all at once in different parts of our
community that we need to think about
waterfall effects in neighborhoods, safe
streets to schools, sidewalks, those
kinds of things. And we need to look at
bigger transportation improvements. And
so this morning, uh, Director Darren
Westby of Y Dot uh, and myself convened
a meeting of your subject matter experts
in the city, the county, and the state.
And I apologize that Mr. hub wasn't
invited, but your MBO folks were there
along with uh county engineer uh along
with u many many white dot employees and
we had a very robust conversation. Mayor
Collins and chief of staff Ash attended
and we talked about what are the
pressure points on the transportation
system right now. Where are things um
most needed, right? uh the south side of
town clearly identified and so your MO
folks are looking at putting together an
RFP out to do a southwest Cheyenne
transportation plan and they're going to
be looking at specifically working with
leads to identify all of these regional
projects. The Lumis family actually
participated in the meeting along with
their consultants to talk about things
like the development of Loving Trail to
talk about the things of the east build
out of the High Plains Road connecting
to College Drive going north to highway
or to Interstate 80. And so taking the
pressure off of these existing
transportation corridors. Now I will
tell you this is going to be um a little
bit time consuming but Cheyenne Leeds is
willing to make a commitment. We're
considering investing over a million
dollars in the 100% design of the High
Plains Road, the last two miles of High
Plains Road going west to the um visitor
center so that you have an alternate
route from I25 over to Highway 85 so
that people can make that transition or
that construction traffic can be taken
off of Terry Ranch Road. And so I would
commend uh councelor Wolf for proposing
that we get to work on a community
benefit agreement, but I would
discourage you from holding up this
project, but I would also encourage you
to support the mayor and his staff in
working cooperatively not only with the
county staff and the state staff in this
subject matter area, but also to work
with the companies themselves because we
can't just ask one company to pay for
all those impacts. We need to bring all
those companies, not just data centers
and not just gas plants or power
generation projects. They need to come
together and work together. And we
already have a model at Cheyenne Leads
where they escrow money for us and then
we actually let the bids and put the
projects in place. So the models there.
You're exactly correct. And I think
Heather gave us some great list of
projects that she needs she would like
to see happen in her community. Dante's
already been communicating with Mr.
Bloom and Mr. Cobb on that nature of
that neighborhood and that development.
And so, um, I just want to let you know
and reassure you that we heard the
community and those public hearing
processes. The process worked.
Congratulations. Uh, it got us talking
about important things that we need to
talk about. Uh I have asked the board of
public utilities to do a similar uh
process to bring us those kinds of
regional uh sewer and water
infrastructure projects. Those lists are
being made. I know the directors here
and also Mr. Strong. Uh so we're all in
the loop here. Uh, so I just want to
reassure you that we heard the public
and we want to move forward with good
ideas and I just encourage other people
um to continue to bring us those good
ideas so that we can collectively
uh make these improvements not just one
company at a time. Thank you.
>> Thank you.
>> Any other public comment? Did you have a
question for Absolutely. I'm sorry.
There's a question for you, Miss Hails.
Thank you, Betsy Hail. It uh
it's fascinating to see the progress
that's being made here, which I think is
the whole reason we have this type of a
meeting and that we have this type of a
process. I would say that uh you know,
I'm a proud member of leads as an
individual. I believe in what you do.
I'm familiar with uh the process going
back to uh the original business park
and how that all came to be. So, it's a
complex matter that's continued for a
number of years.
I think it's reached a boiling point.
Did you say that this meeting happened
this morning you're referring to? Mhm.
>> Was there any consideration of inviting
the members of the council to that
meeting?
>> Actually, we had that discussion with
the mayor. We wanted to have an
opportunity for um the subject matter
experts to take the stage, the folks
that have really studied these
transportation barriers, the challenges
that have been able to say, "Here's a
priority on Terry Ranch. Here's a
priority on uh Highway 85 and the
intersection of College Drive." So, we
were in an information gathering mode
because I'm not a transportation
engineer. I'm not a transportation
expert. And so, I don't think there was
any intentional slight uh to not invite
the council because the conversation I
actually asked the mayor, how do you
want to present this to council? And
what he would like to do is have more
meat on the bones rather than just have
a big visionary laundry list of
projects. He would actually like to have
numbers to discuss because the companies
and I can tell you on High Plains Road
in our conversation on the overpass. I
have a company that would be interested
in helping us build the High Plains
overpass over the BNSF Railroad and you
know that's not cheap with Christensen
Road, right? And also the two miles of
road. But if I don't have a number, a
budget number, I'm just asking, right?
And so rather than bring you a wish
list, um we also want to make sure that
we do projects that are tangible and
impactful for larger parts of the
community. But I can also tell you that
I do have a meeting with um Peaches
Terrell this week to talk about the Mory
Brown uh foundation and their proposal
of the rec center. I think it's
important again everybody brings a
little bit to the table. everybody
understands how we can work together,
not just one data center company, not
just one power generation company. Bring
everyone to the table to solve things on
a much bigger regional basis. And
really, if you think about it, prior to
this year or prior to the meta project,
we were doing things one project at a
time and we weren't anticipating what
waterfall effects would come and we
weren't anticipating more companies
looking at Cheyenne. And so I think now
to your point, yes, councelor Lebornne
and Madam Chair, through you my
apologies. Um,
we're there. were there and we've heard
you and we've heard your constituents
and so my suggestion again is let's let
the process work. It's worked great for
six years on the other projects that
we've done. We want to expand it to
include other industries, other
companies. Uh we want to layer that
public private philanthropic
partnership. You know, as I said,
leadeds is putting our financial
resources into this and um so yes, sir.
I I think we may be a little bit late to
the dance, but I'd really like to catch
up.
>> Thank you. Um I do have a comment or
two. I think that uh this is
exactly what uh we need. No doubt about
that.
um exactly how it gets spread and how we
evaluate that um
is my question. And certainly um in this
comments that we just heard, uh the idea
seems to be that those of us that have
to make this decision
right now
um
will get this information later.
And that information is critical,
critical information
that speaks to the condition of our
city, not another city, not another
water system,
not somewhere else. the specifics of our
city and South Cheyenne,
which of course has its own
uh unique sort of sewer and water system
that is uh uh very much a
um continuing effort. And I also think
that when you look at that
transportation network uh and certainly
I'm aware of what is now the largest uh
signalization in the state of Wyoming.
You just go up South Gy Highway,
I don't know, half a mile and that
signalization is sitting on telephone
poles as a temporary
and that's significant.
We're playing catchup
with the ball that's rolling fast in
South Cheyenne with a number of these
issues. And I can just tell you, I
understand you didn't call this meeting,
but everything that I'm hearing from
you, Miss Hails, is exactly what we're
suggesting
in regard to this one particular
development
because we have to take into
consideration all of the other
developments
that are going to be impacting here. And
that's really the point of my particular
choice of my vote on this annexation.
It's the bigger picture
and it is one that uh is particularly
clouded and I I just want to mention
this madame chairman because it is
relevant very relevant to this
discussion and that is the planning
commission and the split between the
planning commission of the city and the
planning commission of the county for
instance.
Would it be appropriate to uh ask a
question of leads as to uh their
relationship with tall grass?
>> Well, we So, Councilman Lebornne, I just
want to make sure that we we don't get
off topic. So, um if it's gerine to the
annexation of this,
>> I'm trying to respond to the very
concerns that are brought forward here
at this at this very meeting.
>> Okay. I just want to make sure that
we're sticking to the lumus annexation.
>> I think it's clear
that not only are myself and my fellow
sponsors
concerned about the big picture,
how those transportation networks are
going to evolve in especially in such
rapid development. I mean this is not
old Cheyenne way we're doing things. Um,
so that discussion comes forward and we
hear it from uh leads.
>> Okay. just
but then
>> you're stepping outside that to ask a
question about the other this is the
point
madam chairman
>> if these business parks
take on that responsibility that in the
case of something that occurs out in the
county is a
>> point of order I don't understand how
this has anything to do with the
annexation what's happening in the
county This is specific to our
annexation.
>> So if we if we can stick to the
Microsoft annexation, I know we've
wandered and we've allowed a lot of
latitude with Councilman Wolf and with
the leads conversation, but we do have
other people that are waiting in the
audience and online to make comments on
this annexation. And I believe that um
there may be opportunities as we move
through the agenda, Councilman Lebornne,
to um ask some of these questions.
Thank you. I I I the point I would make
is
we've got a lot to decide. We've got a
lot of absolutely unprecedented
and
unknown factors here from a number of
different
corporations,
different land owners. But there's one
thing that's clear.
We would benefit
from our effort here to
make sure that we really understand and
deal with this particular
>> Madame Chair. I can answer that question
if it's if you would allow me and I'll
be brief. We actually have participated
in all of the meetings with tall grass
and with white dot uh in those
conversations and three projects uh will
be posed to tall grass to address their
impacts to transportation and then some
of the nexuses that might involve other
companies. So that similar conversation
is happening within the county and we
had a great uh feedback from the county
uh planning director uh to discuss how
he'll be looking at community benefit
agreements and working with the county
commissioner. So yes, you're all you're
all running in parallel and as as if you
can give us just a couple weeks to kind
of flush out a timeline, flush out the
discussion, work on cost allocations
like you're talking about, I think we
can get you a little more comfortable
and address some of the concerns that uh
um councelor Wolf has. So um but thank
you and thank you for allowing me some
extra time.
>> And so this would be a leadsled effort
>> through the chair, please.
>> Madam Chair,
Madam chair through you can ask a
question or statement there.
>> We are in a better position as a
nonprofit organization to bring all the
parties to the table because we also
have to bring the data centers and the
gas generation companies and all the
other companies that might participate
to the table. And so that there's a lot
of um moving parts if you will. Um, but
again, one of the things I always hear
from Board of Public Utilities is they
try to treat everyone the same. The
rules are the same for everyone. We want
to make sure the rules are the same for
everyone, but we also want to give you a
playbook and we want to give the mayor a
playbook of what the projects could be.
And then to your question, how do they
get paid for? Cost allocation is going
to be a big part of that formula. How do
those cost sharings get allocated? So,
it's not going to be quick. I can't
promise you quick. I can't promise you a
quick turnaround. But I can promise you
that it is there's a commitment on your
no staff part. There's a commitment on
your other city staff. I think there's a
commitment from the city and the county
leadership and and team and also from W
dot and the governor's office to do
things the Wyoming way. And so I I I
want to share with you madam chair and
members of the committee that um we
heard your citizens and we want to do
things in a very wellthoughtout manner
so that when you do negotiate these
agreements you are having impactful
projects successfully done.
>> Thank you.
Any other Did you have another question
Councilman L? It's Germaine. Well, I I I
believe it's Germaine to comment to to
comment on what was just brought before
us. It's not uh I didn't ask uh Miss
Hails to come and make that report. She
did. I think that when that she makes
that report, it becomes relevant to our
discussion. That's not something I'm
bringing an irrelevancy to.
>> Did you have a question?
I have a statement. Okay. They want to
make a statement.
>> Um very we still have people waiting to
make public comments. So please do it
quickly so that because you the
committee will still have time to make
comments.
>> Well, this sure sounds good and I'm glad
to hear it. Thank you.
>> Okay. Other public comment.
>> Good afternoon. Good afternoon. I'm
Donna Dundan, 112 West 4th Avenue here
in Cheyenne. Um, excuse me. I wasn't
prepared for such an open session. I
thought I'd have my, you know, two less
than three minutes to you will after
this topic after this item. So,
>> um, but what too much has opened here.
What I loved was I loved Mrs. Hail's
comments here. She said she can't
promise you quick and give them couple
weeks and that they want to do things
the Wyoming way. And they she also said
she wants impactful projects for s to be
successfully done. So I'm asking you as
a concerned citizen since they're not
ready and they're the professionals, can
we just take our time as well? Can we
not rush this? There's no profit in it
for us. All we want is a community
that's going to be sound, safe. We want
a
governing board that we believe in and
we can support and we don't lose faith
in. We we want to value your opinions.
We want to see Cheyenne grow. Um we'd
love to see Cheyenne grow, but we want
to see it grow in a steady and healthy
manner. Um, unlike the leads, we don't
have a state representative with stake
in the game. Okay? There's no profit
coming off on our end. We don't have a
bottom line, a margin that we're looking
for profitability. There's people on the
leads board that do have that in mind.
They do want to rush the project. They
will benefit from the project. We want
to all benefit from a well-designed
developed project here in Cheyenne. that
is safe, that is sound, that is showing
us how in the years to come, that they
have taken into account how it's going
to affect Cheyenne. Are we going to lift
it up? Um, if something goes wrong, what
are the things that can go wrong? How
would we address them? I think we need a
little bit more time and not rush it.
Just like they said, they need more time
to come up with solid answers for
themselves.
And that's exactly what we need. We need
more time. Um the annexation, I
understand. Um but if you look at the
bottom line of their rush, there's
federal incentives and federal rebates
that they're all in a rush for. And this
is data data centers uh nationwide. And
with that rush, there's also um uh
production slowdowns and production
hindrances in the equipment they need to
build safe facilities. They can't get
the generators they want. They can't get
the parts that they all need right away.
Those are in backup. There's um people
bidding to get at the top of a line to
get those parts. We don't know what they
have. We don't know what they need. We
don't know how close they want to be to
getting those federal rebates. Their
their urgency is not our problem. If
this is what they do and they do it as
professionals and they do it as um
ongoing all the time, this is their gig.
I'm not that's not what I do as a
professional. You know, this is not me.
So, I don't know all of the specifics
and the nuances to it, but they do. and
they've been doing this a long time. Why
aren't they ready?
Why aren't they ready? Like the simple
questions and like I said, their urgency
is is not our urgency. We're we're going
to be here. We'll work with them, but
we're not in that much of a hurry. We
want to do it right. And we want to do
it so that we don't lose faith in the
Cheyenne government, that we do keep our
integrity because for Cheyenne, we're a
small community. And the reason I moved
here was because of that community and I
try to be a helpful contributing member
to society and I am evolv involved and
active in our society and I think that
um if we want to see Cheyenne grow as a
leader um we don't want to be a sad
statistic like we're seeing so many
cities in the states around the uh our
country right now because of the data
centers and because of their broad
terminology. They have this vague
dialogue, this vague language that they
keep putting it out there, but we don't
have the definitives. Where else can we
talk like that? I can't come to you and
say, "Hey, I'm I I need to put this
thing on my house. I need you to give me
the rights to do that." You like,
"What?" Well, I don't know. It could be
10 feet. It could be 25 feet.
Well, how far is it from the property
line? I'm not sure. Maybe two feet,
maybe five feet.
You're going to ask specifics for me to
build and add on to my property, right?
Same here. Let's just go slow. It's our
city. It's not just our property. It's
our city.
So, please just consider, take your
time, and their their urgency is not
ours. We have time, and we want a
partnership, but we want a good
partnership. We want a solid partnership
with people with
transparency and integrity and knowledge
and who know what they're doing and are
ready to just talk about it, show it,
and explain it when they're ready. I
thank you.
>> Thank you.
Any other public comment?
I see we have Mr. Miller.
Uh, can you hear me?
>> Yes, we can. We
>> can.
>> Okay. Just give me a couple of seconds
here.
>> Just for your information, Mr. Miller,
there is not a threeminute clock running
right now, but there will be after this
item. Um, so use your time accordingly.
>> All righty.
And I'm sorry I I actually joined the
meeting uh a little bit uh late. So um
could you would you mind referencing the
agenda item that you're on
>> 14
on the and we're well we haven't even
gotten to the amendment yet.
>> We that was my error. And so that
amendment is uh the amendment I jumped
on right when Councilman Wolf was
describing is his amendment is his
suggested amendment. Is that what you're
talking about?
>> His suggested his suggested amendment is
that it would delay it until December uh
in order to allow the mayor to um and
his staff to do community agreements uh
community benefit statement. And so that
amendment itself is uh on today's agenda
or
>> no the amendment has not been made yet.
We are still actually on the original
motion. It was my eron allowing that
conversation to go forward before we had
a motion in an amendment.
>> Hey well it's not always an error. Um
but uh okay thank you. Uh let's see
here. The
All right. Let me just get up to snuff
here. Um okay. So, I'm going to try to
keep it to uh reasonable time. I don't
intend on going too much over 3 minutes.
Uh
>> let's see here. Um
okay.
Um
Madame Chair, members of the public
services committee, for the permanent
administrative record, my name is
Charles Miller. I am entering the July
6th, 2026 public services committee
agenda into the record as exhibit A. Um
I can uh email that to you guys there or
or upload it into the chat, but you guys
have it as well. Um, but at the top of
this official agenda, the city of
Cheyenne states in writing, "Any
supporting document affiliated with an
agenda item is the document as initially
submitted for the agenda and may not
include any proposed amendments or
revisions.
This is the city's own admission that
the documents provided to the public um
for items 14, 15, and 16, the 3500 acre
Microsoft Highlands annexation and
business park zoning are incomplete by
design. This committee is acting in a
quasi judicial capacity. When the public
services committee holds a hearing,
takes public comment and makes a
recommendation on parcel specific
annexation and zoning ordinances, it is
performing an adjudicary function.
Uh the full city council relies on this
committee's recommendation. Therefore,
this committee must ensure the record is
complete, that the public has a has a
meaningful opportunity to review and
respond to the actual documents under
consideration, and that its
recommendation is supported by a genuine
analytical bridge between the evidence
and the decision. You cannot satisfy
those requirements when the city's own
agenda declares that the documents the
public received may not include any
proposed amendments or revisions. uh the
public is for being forced to commit to
comment on an incomplete record while
this committee considers advancing the
largest industrial annexation in
Cheyenne's history.
Um earlier in this meeting, Councilman
Wolf addressed this committee and
admitted on the record that annexation
is the thing Microsoft really wants. He
stated that even his own proposal is a
compromise that is less effective than
postponing any decision for 5 months. He
confirmed that he is he deliberately
removed all criteria, all minimum
standards, all boundaries, and all
constraints from any community benefit
agreement language. He further admitted
that there is nothing requiring the
mayor to actually negotiate a meaningful
agreement. Those statements are now part
of the permanent record as exhibit B.
This committee is advancing these items
on a record that the city itself admits
is incomplete. While a member of the
city council has openly stated that
meaningful protections have been
stripped out and that the city is giving
Microsoft exactly what it wants. This is
not quasi judicial decision-making. This
is the advancement of a predetermined
outcome on a defective record. This
creates clear reversible error under
Wyoming law. It violates due process and
the standards that govern quas quasi
judicial land use proceedings. Uh you
have been placed on notice that with the
city's own agenda and with the words of
a sitting member of the city council
uh if you choose to advance items 14,
15, and 16 anyway, you are permanently
documenting these defects in the
permanent administrative record. Um now,
excuse me. Now, uh that since I have a a
a little bit of leeway time, I'd kind of
like to go into a little bit of detail
uh in the quasi judicial um uh tribunal
uh
you know, definition there. Um so, give
me one moment. I'll pull that up.
While you're doing that, Mr. Miller, and
looking that up, I would like to go on
record saying that uh these were not
incomplete by design.
Okay.
Um, let's see here.
>> You can talk for an hour if you want to.
>> Okay, here I go. Here I' I've got almost
got it pulled up here. Okay. So,
um,
a governmental body acts in a quasi
judicial capacity when it is applying
existing law or policy to specific facts
or specific property rather than making
broad legislative policy for the entire
community. Examples include deciding
whether to annex a particular piece of
land, assigning or changing zoning on
specific parcels, approving or denying a
specific development proposal. In these
situations, the body is acting more like
a tribunal than a legislature. Quasi
judicial requirements in Wyoming. When a
body, including a city council
committee, um acts in quasi judicial
capacity.
>> Point of order.
>> Yes.
>> This um through you. This is about this
is not about the annexation at all. Mr.
Miller has gone down a rabbit hole as
far as processes that have nothing to do
with the annexation. So, I would ask
that we get back on to the the topic at
hand.
>> Thank you. Mr. Miller, can you take it
back to the annexation item number 14?
>> I I thought that this was uh um
definitely relevant. Um because uh you
you guys are are acting under the wrong
assumption that that you guys can make a
legislative decision on this when uh
when crucially Wyoming uh has already
the Supreme Court has already ruled on
this. uh you guys are holding your
hearings completely uh uh incorrectly
>> and duly noted.
>> So let's talk about number 14.
>> So okay so the so today you're acting in
a quasi judicial capacity on items 14 15
and 16 because you're holding a hearing
on parcel specific annexation and zoning
ordinances the 3500 acre highlands
project. Um, and because you're taking
public comment and because you're making
a formal recommendation that the full
city council will rely on for third
reading and final action. These are
individualized determinations about
specific land, not general citywide
policy. Because you're acting in a quasi
judicial function, it is legally
required that you ensure that the public
has has access to the complete and
actual documents being considered and
that there is meaningful opportunity to
comment on the real proposal and that it
most importantly I think here uh that
your recommendation is supported by an
analytical bridge between evidence and
decision. Um
now,
uh
that's uh the these requirements are
grounded in due process in Wyoming law,
including Wyoming statute 16-3-114.
Um and with that, I uh I will pass it
back to you guys. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Mr. Miller. I see Mr. Moody
has his hand raised.
We're on item number 14, Mr. Moody.
>> All right. Thank you, Madam Chair. Mark
Moody, Shine State City Council W three.
I won't repeat what everybody said, but
um Mr. Wolf said right on a point my
colleague from Ward One. I just think I
don't see what the harm is in doing a
delay.
It should be longer. But again, we need
to look at the long-term ramifications,
not just short term. And again this will
also too
from a uh from the public's perspective
regarding what happened with meta and
with the bopu report this needs to be
taken into account as well. So that's
why I would when we do the amendments
just delay happy to take questions.
>> Thank you. Okay. Uh Mr. Labour did you
have a question?
>> Yes I did. Uh, Madame Chair, is the uh,
city attorney's office monitoring this
meeting online?
>> I saw Mr. Brody online earlier.
>> Did you have a question for him? He's
online.
>> Go ahead and ask your question.
>> Mr. Brody, we just heard a whole series
of uh
very interesting use of legal language
and some statements as to what courts
have ruled and what statute is relevant.
I think that uh
these attacks on our system are uh
something that needs to be noted.
Um
we talk about
the various elements of speaking to the
motion. Obviously
uh this is not the case and um I've
discussed this with you in the past Mr.
Brody and I intend to pursue it further.
I don't believe that this is a a useful
u use of our time. I don't believe that
Mr. uh Miller's accusations
have any bearing whatsoever.
And so I'm I'm very much of the belief
that here in this important decision
that we're trying to make here today, we
have uh that kind of irrelevancy and uh
real fundamental attacks on the way we
run our city and the way we have these
meetings. And I I I just want that noted
because I'm definitely going to be
pursuing this further. It's uh something
that we need to pay attention to. Uh
this discussion we're attempting to have
here today is to be based on reality.
It's to be based on the law and it is to
be based on public participation.
uh this uh has just really slipped
completely out of control, Madame
Chairman, and I think that we need some
answers as to why this individual
continually
brings these matters up when there's no
if there's any factual basis, Mr. Brody,
I'd sure like to know it, and maybe you
could help me with that.
>> Mr. Brody, is there any factual basis
for the comments that were made by Mr.
Miller?
Madame Chairman, John Brody, city
attorney. I I I guess some um I guess I
would say that my office's research and
the case law we've seen shows that
annexation is clearly a legislative act,
not quasi judicial. Um I'm happy to
discuss this further with council, but
um I generally refrain from providing
legal advice uh in a public forum.
>> Thank you. Okay, we are on item 14. Um
and so is there any uh further public
comment? I don't see any hands raised
nor anyone here. Okay, we are going to
close public comment. Um and we are on
item 14, not on the amendment. Um my
apologies uh because I let this take off
and a conversation about the amendment
before we ever had a motion. So I would
entertain a motion on item number 14.
Madame Chairwoman, I would move to
approve on third reading. Okay,
>> we have a motion from Dr. Renie.
>> Second.
>> We have a second from Dr. Emmens. Is
there any discussion?
>> Madame Chairman.
>> Yes.
I move that we deate delete section five
of this annexation action and substitute
uh amended section to read
that that this ordinance shall be in
full force in effect on December 31st,
2026. The purpose of the delayed
effective date is to allow the mayor and
staff time to negotiate a community
benefit agreement with Microsoft
Incorporated.
>> Okay, we have an amendment to delete
section five and to substitute uh what
Mr. Councilman Lelay just read. Is there
a second?
>> Madam Chairwoman,
so that the councilman may discuss it, I
will second it.
>> Okay, we have a second by Dr. Renie. Um,
we will now go out for public comment on
the amendment. Um, if you've already
spoken on the amendment, I would
encourage you to please uh limit your
conversation to the amendment. We are
starting the threeminut timer with this
item. Is there any public comment?
Looks like we have someone um Mr. Nicely
has his hand up.
>> Yeah, David Nicely 200 Wshot. Um I
believe the testimony of uh Cheyenne
Leeds suggests that Mr. Mood Moody's
original proposal of a moratorum across
the spectrum was a good motion.
Cheyenne Leis has testified that we need
to not be sight specific but be
comprehensive.
It's uh apparent to me that the ducks
are not in a row um across the spectrum
of Cheyenne planning regarding any of
the industries.
Um we've spent public funds to attract
and promote industry that we're not
prepared to support.
Um, we need to have a conversation as a
community about how to spend our social
resources and how to allocate the
potential gains from them.
I'm not generally in favor of social
um, planning.
Um, I agree with Dr. Renie when he said
that it's a property rights issue that
this family should be able to do with
their property what they want to. I
think that applies beyond the Lumis
family. I hope you'll remember that in
November 9th. What once
public money is spent
and is proposed
to support these data centers, the
public has a right
to speak on how that those resources are
used.
So if we would go back to Adam Smith in
a lace fair approach,
um I'm all for letting industry do what
industry wants to do and let the
invisible hand govern it.
But if we're going to pursue this quasi
socialism the city of Cheyenne is
pursuing through its central planning,
then the sky's the limit. We have
another problem.
Many in the public don't trust the city
government or the corporates.
At least one city councilman has told us
that he doesn't trust us either.
In the context of distrust, we should
certainly
pause and rebuild trust and have a
conversation.
I think we probably should have a
moratorum on anything but minimum city
actions until such trust is formed.
certainly until after the election. Um,
that's my stake. Um, you'll do what
you'll what you do. The ducks aren't in
a row. Paul,
>> thank you.
>> Okay, Mr. Miller, can you please keep
this germaine only to the amendment and
you have three minutes.
Um yes I will I will try to do that. Um
just one moment here. Can you hear me?
>> We can.
>> All right.
Um and this is the amendment that uh Mr.
Leborn had just proposed. Is that
correct?
>> That's correct.
>> All right. Uh, Madame Chair, members of
the committee for the permanent
administrative record, my name is
Charles Miller. I'm issuing a formal
constructive notice regarding the fatal
procedural and fiduciary defects of the
amendment currently on the floor. First,
the introduction of this un unagendized
amendment perfectly validates the due
process violation I placed on the record
earlier. You are you are conducting a
quasi judicial hearing. Yet you are
attempting to delete section 5 and bolt
on a completely new December 31st
effective date that was hidden from the
published public packet. You cannot
legally ambush the taxpayers with
substance substantive floor amendments
in a in an adjudicary proceeding.
Second, the uh the transcript of this
very meeting proves this amendment is a
political charade designed to grant a
trillion dollar developer everything
they want while legally guaranteeing
nothing for the citizens of Cheyenne.
Councilman Wolf explicitly confessed on
the live microphone that this is a
simple two-s sentence amendment that
sets no conditions, no boundaries, no
constraints on the negotiations. Dr.
Renie correctly identified the fatal
loophole, admitting on the record that
this language does not mandate the mayor
to do that and that the mayor could
choose not to negotiate. Councilman Wolf
agreed, acknowledging the mayor could
simply walk away and say, "I either
can't do it or I won't do it." You are
attempting to mask a multi-billion
dollar land grab behind a completely
toothless suggestion. Finally, a delay a
delayed effective date of December 31st
does not cure your violation of the
Tonga doctrine. You are still voting
today to advance a 3500 acre ghost
project that lacks any hydraological
telemetry, thermal engineering data, or
finalized site plans. A statutory
defective ordinance passed today does
not magically become lawful on December
31st just because you plan to hold
closed door meetings in the interim. If
you vote yes on this amendment, you are
officially passing a broken document and
locking in your legal liability. You
have been formally warned. I demand a
motion to deny both this unagendized
amendment and the underlying ordinance.
Thank you.
>> Thank you. I see uh Heather with your
hand raised.
Can you are can you hear me? Okay,
>> we can and we are on item 14 on the
amendment only.
>> Okay, thank you. Um I I support this
amendment. I think that we anything to
buy the community a little bit of time
um and hopefully time to have
a better plan for this annexation
because
currently I my belief is that this is
arbitrary and capriccious because
there's no plan at all. Um, I
would
just like to read a quote from James
Madison.
There is an evil which ought to be
guarded against any indefinite
accumulation of property from the
capacity of holding it in perpetuity by
corporations. The power of all
corporations ought to be limited in this
respect. The growing wealth acquired by
them never fails to be a source of
abuses.
And I think we should heed that warning.
Um and again I I fully support this this
amendment to um delay the date of
effect. Thank you.
>> Thank you.
Is there any other public comment?
>> Hey hearing or seeing none um we'll come
back to the uh dis.
Any discussion on the amendment?
Councilman Lebornne.
>> Well, uh, first of all, I want to thank
Dr. Renie for his, uh, second here for
the purpose of discussion. I think
that's, uh, something I deeply
appreciate and believe is important. I
understand that that's, uh,
only for that purpose and I think that's
a worthy purpose.
And I think that this right now is uh
something that
uh we need to consider carefully. And
one of the factors that I consider
carefully in this discussion is the
experience
and the knowledge that my colleague
Larry Wolf brings to this process.
It's not like what I understand, what I
practice in city government. it's uh a
lifetime of experience in these matters
and so I think that that's uh worthy of
some consideration.
I'd also point out the testimony that we
just heard here a few moments ago
from uh
Betsy Hail and Leadeds
about the ongoing effort that
in my opinion should have preceded this.
But uh nevertheless, as I commented,
uh that South Cheyenne and its
transportation network and its
sewer and water network and its uh whole
relationship to the city, the people
that live there is uh very much under
consideration. And I think that that's
uh very important that we hear what just
was testified to. There's a lot to know.
There's a lot to study.
And this really would give us the time
to do it. If this is the the will of the
body to do the annexation,
so be it.
To believe that all those factors that
of course was brought up earlier by
Councilman Wolf uh don't come into play.
Um
not realistic.
This is something that is very close to
what happened with the annexation
agreement
with the sweet grass annexation with the
same property owner in the same location
on the adjacent property.
Not.
I believe that that is a very relevant
decision that the property owner made
that had good reason for that to occur.
And we've seen as time went on that uh
that has been referenced and dealt with
in a number of ways to change or modify
some of those conditions. But there's a
framework to go to. There's a framework
there that's very important. So,
I hope that uh
some of the people that seem to be
opposed to uh this action would
tell us why and tell us how
uh all of this is going to come together
because I think it's clear from the
public testimony and certainly from
everything we experience when we're out
in the community, there's a great
interest in this
very unique matter.
and one that uh moves beyond the
boundaries of this particular
annexation.
And I think that that's our
responsibility is to take a look at that
to work with uh the people that want to
do it. I'm I'm disappointed that uh
the mayor didn't want uh any of the
council people evidently to come to the
meeting this morning. Uh I'm sure I
would have learned something.
Um, and I think that that's part of this
whole process.
It's uh
difficult for council people to sort
through this whole history and how it's
come about and why it's uh the way it is
now. I see we just got the comments from
the planning commission. We'll be
getting to that a little later here, but
there's good reason for us to uh
pay close attention
and to act on this amendment.
Thank you,
>> Dr. Rmans.
>> Thank you, Madam Chairman. Um, I'm going
to speak against this amendment for
several very specific ideas. First of
all, for anybody to say we've not been
transparent and they've not had an
opportunity to be heard has not been
paying attention. We have taken so much
testimony. We've listened to so many
people. We have read every single email.
We have we've had the testimony. We've
listened. And I I appreciate the fact
that
um
some people don't like the decisions
we're making, but we've made them based
on full information. So that's one
thing. Second thing, you know, we
complain about business at the speed of
government rather than at the speed of
business. I've heard that repeatedly
since I came on the council that we slow
everything down. We stand in the way of
progress. We stand in the way of
building. We stand in the way of getting
things done. But here we are once again
doing business at the speed of
government.
Um I think that um
the fact that we're targeting one
company, not even one industry, but one
company feels very arbitrary and
capriccious, which bothers me and
worries me as far as potential legal
issues.
Um the fact that we have an amendment
with no results, no goals tied to it
doesn't make sense to me. there's a
difference between negotiating an
agreement and negotiating an outcome or
some goals. So that that doesn't make
sense to me as far as good governance.
Um
and um the pause issue, we have heard
the pause issue. We've dealt with the
pause issue now I don't know 10 times
maybe that we've brought this forward
again and again and again and again and
the council has voted continuously no on
the pause. So why do we keep bringing it
back? Um, I think that makes us look
incredibly inefficient and ineffective.
Maybe not inefficient, ineffective, that
we've made it clear we are trusting
these people who have been in this
community for 14 years to continue doing
what they've done. They they are the
number one taxpayer in the community.
They have put tons of money into the
college, into education, into the
community. But we're saying that's not
enough. I I just don't get that. So
based on the fact that I feel like this
is just one more work around for a
pause, I'm going to vote no on this
amendment.
Any other discussion by committee
hearing? None. All in favor of the
amendment say I.
>> I.
>> All opposed.
>> No.
>> Okay. That the amendment fails. We are
back on the main motion. Um, and so we
um will take public comment on Do we
don't need to go back to public comment?
Okay. Sorry, Mr. White. We've already
had public comment on this one.
>> Uh, thank you, M. Madam Chairman. Then
I'll just wait for the next item.
>> You're a man of patience. We appreciate
it. Okay. So, we're back on the main
menu. Any discussion by committee? Dr.
Renie. Madam Chairwoman, a couple things
I want wanted to address or point out
and that is um it's been referred to the
fact well first of all um
the second largest annexation by the
city was Sweetg Grass which is about
twothirds the size of this and was of
the same owners and it's been pointed
out um that SweetGrass had some very
welldefined
um criteria that was
um with it when it was annexed and that
there was a lot of negotiation and a lot
of um things attached to that. But some
of that was that SweetGrass was a
planned unit development and that
requires and that's a whole they have
their own set of essentially set of
rules and own set of zoning codes. So
there is some um extra
um additional negotiations and and
decisions made up front in the case of
that. And the other thing that in regard
to Sweetgrass when we annexed it, I
don't think we knew exactly how many
homes were going to be built there and
we didn't know how many businesses were
going to be um located in their
commercial area. it it has been a work
in progress and we have amended it
several times since its initial
annexation. So I don't see why in this
case with the highlands
why we are now expected to treat it
differently than we treated the
companion residential area. So um I will
be obviously um be supporting the
annexation. Thank you madam chairwoman.
Thank you. Councilman Labbourne, did you
have a comment?
>> Yes, I did. And uh this comment is uh
in regard to this annexation, obviously
in regard to uh
exactly what's going to happen here
with this annexation.
And I want to note that uh
however we
want to uh
talk about what we do here and how we do
it, it is an established process.
It is something that is follow state law
and I'd like to speak to that. Um this
is not um
this is my interpretation my
understanding of this allimportant
matter
and one of the things that is obviously
a part of the annexation review criteria
is the annexation of the areas for the
protection of the health, safety and
welfare of the persons residing in the
area and in the city or town.
Okay. Well, some people might look at
that differently than I, but I look at
that as the uh basic reasoning that the
state gives us for taking a look at
that.
and I and obviously uh quite a number of
other people especially out in the
community
um are wondering how uh this matter
relates to their
safety and welfare health in uh they do
reside in this city
and more than anything else uh the point
that I want to make here
is the area sought to be annexed as a
logic ical and feasible addition to the
annexing city.
An extension of basic and other services
customarily available to residents of
the city or town shall within reason be
available to the area proposed to be
annexed.
So maybe some of my other colleagues
here look at this uh differently.
I look at it based on my experience and
knowledge of Ward One, which does
definitely come down involve
a lot of the property both uh that we
have annexed in the fairly recent past
what we're considering here today. And I
don't believe it's logical.
I don't believe it's logical to
take a look at this annexation
cut out by itself.
I think if it's feasible,
we need to consider all those services
and how they come into that uh property.
So although we've heard a lot of
discussion and a lot of we're going to
we're going to hear some more here from
the planning commission's report shortly
but I just believe that when we look at
that it's up to us to interpret it.
It isn't up to the staff to interpret it
for us.
It isn't up to another council person to
interpret it for us.
It's up to us to take this deep
responsibility
to look at this
based on our experience and judgment.
And when I do,
I don't see the lo overall logic.
I see a intense
movement uh in ways that
are becoming a little more clear thanks
to some of the testimony we heard here
today, but definitely not really clear
in terms of uh how much and how many. It
seems it it how is it logical
that we're to exclude
another
massive project
just proposed in this same vicinity for
the same purpose? How is it logical that
we look at that and say, "Oh,
that's not related to uh the project
few miles away. That's not related to
our annexation actions. That's not
related to our ability to provide water.
I believe it is and that's the reason
that I'm going to be voting uh
in committee here and I expect without
some real meaningful changes and
discussion
at the final meeting uh next week
because
there's a lot of complexity here.
There's a lot of issues that uh
might be interpreted one way or might be
interpreted another way. But there is a
tremendous
tremendous change happening
coming right now to the city of Cheyenne
that'll
really really bring some wonderful
things
and some funds and some taxes
and it'll bring some other things that a
gold rush type atmosphere brings.
This is not
comparable to the other annexations we
did for the other business parks.
It's not as big. It's not as related.
So, those are the reasons that I'm
voting no. And I want them noted that uh
uh it just isn't a feeling that I have.
It's a belief in those annexation review
criteria
and how I take them seriously in the
belief that
as we heard earlier, there are ways
these things can be worked out and
improved and we're going to need to do
it as fast and as thoroughly as we can.
But let's be realistic about what we're
really doing here. And I think when we
when we look at that we see that uh this
massive change can't be considered in
isolation.
It's not in isolation
and it won't be in isolation as time
goes on without us knowing what those
criteria are. So uh thank you for your
time. I appreciate uh the opportunity to
discuss these issues and uh looks
forward to the continuing discussion.
Thank you. Any other discussion from
committee?
All in favor of the motion say I.
>> I.
>> All opposed.
>> No.
>> This item will move forward with our
recommendation to approve at the next
meeting of the council. Next item,
please. Number 15, ordinance third
reading, amending the official zoning
map of the city of Cheyenne,
establishing the zoning classification
of AG agricultural for land annex to the
city of Cheyenne located east of South
Gley highway and south of the Sweet
Grass subdivision.
>> Staff report please.
>> Madam Chair, members of the committee,
Conor Planning and Development
Department, um Ken, with any annexation,
there is an assigned zoning. Staff's
recommendation for the annexation is to
assign at the AG zone. like to remind
the committee that even with the next
item, it does not propose reszoning the
entirety of the 3500 acre annexation.
So, some would be left to AG. So, we no
matter what need the assigned zoning
regardless of what happens on the next
item because any property within the
city needs to have a city zone so we can
actually regulate it. Um, but with that,
staff recommends approval of the
assigned zoning. It was approved on
second reading. Uh, planning commission
recommended approval and I'm available
for any questions. Thank you. Okay. Any
questions from committee for staff?
Okay. We will then go to public comment.
We do have the threeminut timer running.
So, Mr. White, thank you for your
patience.
>> Through you, Madam Chairman. Michael
White.
I'd like this governing body to give me
a little latitude. U
>> You have three minutes of latitude, sir.
Um, I was late cuz my daughter had a
flat tire on the way to Denver today.
But
>> I'd like to still initiate that I don't
believe the rules for um this whole
project have been followed based on
state statute.
and I quote Governor Gordon saying that
he's provided to his staff
recommendations to put a pause on
anything and everything that has to do
with these kind of projects. I find that
interesting.
Um, like I said, give me a little
attitude. Um, we talked about the Cox
Ranch annexation zoning.
this governing body gave
this group and us till September to
continue on with what we would have good
discussion. So I'm a little mythed. I'm
a code person and a standard person
since I got into the trades in 1974.
Um when people make an exception whether
it's code or I believe whether it's
statute or ordinance
that's the rule now. So,
we go back to what has been said where
we've had a lot of public comment. I
don't believe we've had enough public
comment.
When I visited with the individuals from
Microsoft,
I visited with two individuals that were
talking about water. One from Tampa,
Florida, and one from San Francisco.
Neither one of them could tell me
exactly how much they were going to use.
They did realize that anything that has
to do with a closed loop system or
wastewater system, they weren't going to
be allowed to dump that system back into
the BP use uh system. And since then, we
have a project that has been, I would
say, taught in the ability to discharge
what's not allowed by city ordinance
based on BOPU's regulations.
So I come to this committee
to say number one
statute has not been met annexation
zoning mapping period. If you guys can
tell me that and the other comments I've
heard is that our comments need to go to
the state capital. Well, I've already
started that process.
Um, I respectively
like the opportunity that all these
committee people have given me over the
past, but I asked you to postpone and
not
vote today on this and thank you for the
latitude. Thank you.
>> Thank you.
>> Any other public comment?
>> Hey, I see Mr. Miller has his hand
raised. Mr. Miller, you have three
minutes. We're on item number 15 before
you ask.
>> Can you hear me?
>> Yes, we can.
>> Uh, great. Um, Madame Chair, members of
the public services committee for the
permanent administrative record. My name
is Charles Miller. I'm issuing a formal
constructive notice of premeditated
regulatory arbitrage and a fatal
violation of the Tanga doctrine
regarding the ordinance to establish an
agricultural AG assigned zoning
classification for the 3,460 acre
Microsoft Highlands annexation.
You're attempting to launder a trillion
dollar hypers scale industrial complex
through a fake farming classification.
You are assigning AG zoning to 18% of
the city's land mass, fully knowing the
applicant intends to build a massive
data center campus on it. This ordinance
is not a legitimate exercise of zoning
authority. It is a procedural charade
and a jurisdictional Trojan horse
designed to bypass state oversight. I'm
placing into the permanent record the
exact confession of your own planning
department. On June 15th, planner
planner Connor White openly admitted on
the live microphone why staff
recommended this AG zone when everyone
knows a data center is planned. He
stated verbatim, "The reason is if
council annexes it and then doesn't zone
it to BP, it has a city zone. It has a
backup zone. Otherwise, we're annexing,
excuse me, a parcel, not giving it a
zone. So, we have to have that backup
zone." Let the record reflect that the
city planner openly admits you are
applying a false classification simply
to establish a mechanical backup zone.
This confession mathematically destroys
your compliance with the Tanga doctrine
enforced in Wyoming through Wilson
Advisory Committee verse board of county
commissioners. Under the Wyoming
Administrative Procedure Act, a quasi
judicial body must build a genuine
analytical bridge between the raw
evidence and the final decision. You
cannot legally or logically bridge the
gap to make an affirm affirmative
factual finding that agricultural zoning
is appropriate when the developer has
openly confessed their industrial
intentions and when your own staff
admits this AG zone is a mere
administrative fiction. zoning 3,460
acres as a farm while reviewing it as a
tech monopoly's 20-year buildout is an
arbitrary and capricious abuse of
discretion that the district court is
mandated to strike down under Wyoming
statute 16-3-114
C I A Furthermore establishing this
temporary backup zone is the required
first step in your premeditated scheme
to defraud Laramie County of
socioeconomic impact fees
You must assign this fake AG zone to
finalize the annexation, securing
municipal jurisdiction so that you can
immediately flip the parcel to business
park zoning. As planning director
Charles Bloom explicitly confessed
regarding this exact maneuver, utilizing
the business park zoning ensures the
development is exempt from the
industrial sighting committee processes.
By voting yes on this, your time is up.
>> Is there any other public comment? Do
you see um any other hands raised,
Jennifer? I don't see any.
Okay, we will close public comment on
number item number 15, which is the
zoning of this parcel. And um I would
entertain a motion.
>> Madam Chairwoman, I move to approve on
third and final reading.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion from Dr. Emmens and a
second from Dr. Renie. Um is there any
discussion?
>> Madam Chairwoman.
>> Yes.
>> I just want to address something. I Mr.
Miller brings this up every time we do
this and I know he doesn't like our
processes
but I want the public to understand that
under our current the way we handle
annexations is once it's annexed it has
to be assigned a city zone and and our
staff assigns it the zone in the city
that is closest to the existing county
zone and it is automatically so the
zoning ordinance follows the annexation
ordinance if people pay attention and
that's just something that we
automatically do. If the developer does
not like that zone, then they will ask
us to change it to whatever zone they
think is appropriate for what they want
to develop, which is what item 16 is.
So, um, as I said, I'm sorry to sorry to
kind of diverge, but I wanted the public
to understand that this is a normal
process. We're not trying to hide
anything. It's just the way we do
things.
>> Thank you for that clarification, Dr.
Renie. Any other discussion by committee
hearing? None. All in favor say I.
>> I.
>> All opposed?
>> No.
>> Okay. This item will move forward with a
recommendation to approve at the next
meeting of the council. Next item,
please. Number 16, ordinance third
reading, amending the official zoning
map of the city of Cheyenne, changing
the zoning classification for the land
located east of South Gley Highway and
south of the Sweet Grass subdivision
from AG agricultural and PUB planned
unit development to PP business park.
Okay. Staff report.
>> Madam chair, members of committee,
Counterway Planning Development
Department, and Dr. Bernie, thank you
for explaining it that way cuz I was
going to with this item. Um that this is
an applicant requested zone change. The
assigned zoning is not applicant
requested, that is staff assigning a
zone. Um and as Councilman uh Dr. Renie
had mentioned, if the applicant doesn't
like that assigned zone, then they
request a zone for how they want to
develop the land. Um with this zone
change, it is a request to the BP
business park zone. it is not for the
full 3500 acres. It is only for a
portion. Um
the other land would be left in that AG
zone because it keeps getting brought up
that apparently zoning overrides the
industrial sighting committee. Um zoning
does not do that. Um that is actually if
an entity creates a business park that's
not under business park zoning. We could
have called the business park zone
industrial flex zoning. um might have
been a poor choice to call it business
park at this point because people keep
getting it confused. Um but business
park zoning zoning does not override
that. That is down to the actual
definition of what a business park is
from other entities not the city's
zoning code. So by zoning anything
business park, it doesn't overrule um
that committee or that process. uh
zoning basically just gives it a zone
within city limits that then provides
the regulations for that zone district.
So just want to put that on the record
because that keeps getting brought up by
the same individual at every single
meeting. Um
this was approved on second reading.
Staff does recommend approval. I'm
available for any questions.
>> Thank you. Any questions for committee
from committee? Okay. If not, we will go
out for public comment. Is there any
public comment here in the room?
Seeing or hearing none, I see Mr.
Miller, you have your hand raised. You
have three minutes to speak on item
number 16.
>> Can you hear me?
>> I can.
>> Okay. Um, so I had a prepared uh Charles
Miller for the record. Um, I had a
prepared speech for this and then I was
just listening about uh how he rebutted
the fact that this overrides the the
sighting act. Um,
and so
uh I just wanted to quickly touch on
that. Um the
uh I uh I I believe that uh that that's
something that needs to be more fully
explored in terms of uh like um their uh
where it where he's claiming that it
does not bypass the Wyoming Industrial
Sighting Act. Um,
so, uh, I'd like to,
uh, city city planner Connor White's
assertion that this zoning does not
bypass the industrial sighting act is
factually false and directly
contradicted by the permanent
administrative transcript. On June 1st,
planning director Charles Bloom
explicitly confessed on the live
microphone regarding this exact business
park maneuver. It is exempt from the
industrial industrial sighting committee
processes, he says. Furthermore,
Councilman Larry Larry Wolf openly
defended this evasion on June 22nd,
stating verbatim, "The legislature
created this scheme." "Do not allow city
staff to present a semantic illusion to
cover up confessed regulatory arbitrage.
You're actively gerrymandering a
business park boundary to shield a
trillion dollar hyperscaler from state
level environmental review and to
defraud Laramie County taxpayers out of
mandatory socio-economic impact fees.
the scheme is on the record and you are
entirely stripped of plausible
deniability. Now, um
in terms of my already prepared speech,
which I probably have about two minutes
or so, one minute and a half, um
uh you are not applying this zone for
sound urban planning. This is a
calculated scheme to exempt a trillion
dollar hyperscaler from the Wyoming
Industrial Sighting Act. The ISA exists
to mandate state level socio-economic
impact studies and impact assistance
bonds to protect Laram County taxpayers
from massive industrial sprawl. Yet your
own planning director Charles Bloom
explicitly confessed the regulatory
evasion um which I just spoke about. Um
by advancing this BP zoning, you are
knownly participating in a scheme to
defraud uh the taxpayers of Laramie
County out of statemandated impact fees
necessary to mitigate this multi-billion
dollar industrial campus. Second, you
cannot legally advance this zoning
because it requires you to arbitrarily
overrule your own planning commission
without a factual basis. During the June
1st planning commission hearing, the
future land use map amendment required
to support this BP zoning failed to
secure the necessary votes. Because the
map amendment failed, your own planning
staff explicitly stated on the record
due to the failure of the future land.
>> Thank you, Mr. Miller. Your time is up.
Is there any other public comment?
I see Heather, your hand is raised.
>> Yes. Can you guys excuse me hear me?
Okay,
>> we can.
>> Okay. Um I I just I think that
um I have emailed back and forth with
several council the entire council and
individually and
um recently received a response from Mr.
D grave that
if we need to revisit the conversation
about you know proper regulations
then he said that's a different
conversation entirely
and I'm wondering how we start that
conversation because I think that
in my experience
leading teams of individuals and massive
projects in a completely obviously
completely different industry.
The excuse of we're doing it this way
because we've always done it this way is
probably my least favorite
of of any excuse I've ever heard. I
think that these
projects are of massive scale and they
require more thoughtful regulations that
protect people from the risks that we
don't yet know about which is which is
evident with what recently happened with
the wastewater contamination.
uh we don't know what we don't know and
instead of just moving forward full
steam ahead as if we have nothing to
learn
can we exercise a little bit of caution
before we just
reszone a massive amount of land and I'm
not saying never we should should
Microsoft own this property and reszone
but man I think we need a little bit
more information before we just keep
moving forward because we can't plan for
everything and it would be nice to be
able to prevent opposed to react to some
of these things because I mean thank god
Boo caught it when they did but who's to
say that's going to happen again you
know we can't we just we need to know
more before we just reszone and annex
and you know every data center that
wants to come here
um the citizens deserve that at the very
minimum. Thank you.
>> Thank you. Any other public comment?
Okay, we will close public comment. Um,
and I would entertain a motion.
>> Madam, pardon me, Madam Chairwoman. I
would move to approve on third reading.
>> Second. Okay, we have a motion to
approve um by Dr. Renie and a second
from Dr. Emmens. Um, is there any
discussion?
>> Madam Chairwoman?
>> Yes, Dr. Renie. for the permanent public
record. I want to address something and
that is um the allegation that by
putting something in
allowing a data center any other large
business to go into a business park they
are skirting around the the
environmental requirements.
Um yes, a lot of the provisions of the
industrial sighting council do not apply
because we have the bandwidth to look in
our staff to look at what's required and
and tell any incoming large business.
This is what we need to ameliate or take
care of the impacts that you are going
to bring that you're going to cause us.
That's essentially what the industrial
sighting council does. It does not um
being in a business park does not exempt
them from getting their permits from the
DEEQ and the DEEQ issues permits in
regard to air quality, water quality and
hazardous waste and they also refer out
those permits before they approve them
to 18 other agencies.
So,
so being in a date in a business city
zone business park does not I just want
people to understand it does not
exempt a data center or any other large
warehouse whatever
um from getting the required DEEQ
permits in regard to air water and
hazardous waste. Thank you, Madam
Chairwoman.
>> Thank you. Any other comments from
committee? Okay. All in favor say I. I
>> opposed.
>> Okay. This item will move forward with a
recommendation to approve at the next
meeting of the council. I did want to
address um Heather's concern about how
to go about changing regulations if it
is a state statute, which is what our
annexation uh where that comes from.
That would be with your elected
legislators and house of representatives
and senators um at the capital building
that you would need to engage in that
initial conversation with. If it has to
do with city ordinance or regulations,
that would be with a city council
member. And you would need to initiate
that conversation with a city council
member or members in order to have those
uh that information brought forward um
in the in light of an ordinance change
or a revision. So um hopefully that will
answer that question.
Next item number 18. Number 18,
Ordinance, third reading, amending the
official zoning map of the city of
Cheyenne, changing the zoning
classification for land located south of
I80 and east of Kish from AG
Agricultural to BP Business Park.
>> Okay. Uh staff report.
>> Madam Chair, members of the committee,
my name is Seth Lloyd. I'm with the
planning and development department of
the city of Cheyenne. Um the proposal in
front of you is to uh zone some land BP
Business Park. This land is located just
east and northeast of LC. Um, this has
previously been on the agenda. There's
no changes to this particular
application. However, the associated
change to the future land use map
amendment was uh, sorry, to the future
land use map was approved. Um, and I
have not had any public comment on this
item since the June 22nd meeting of the
governing body. I'm available for any
questions on this item.
>> Thank you. Is there are there any
questions for staff?
Okay, hearing none, we'll open it up for
public comment. And Mr. Emmens,
>> um, excuse me, Madam Chairwoman, city
council members Brad Emmens, AVI, as
this is a different parcel of land. just
wanted to come forward um and bring
forward that uh based upon the future
land use amendment and the staff's
agreement that BP is a usable zone in
here. We look forward to uh the BP being
uh selected as the zone for this parcel
of land and happy to answer any
questions of the council.
>> Thank you.
The timer Thank you. Hey Rachel. Hello.
Good afternoon, chair, members of the
public service committee. My name is
Rachel Irwing. I'm the land development
and permitting program manager for
Microsoft. Um, for the record, our
address is one Microsoft Way, Redmond,
Washington. Um, again, I appreciate the
opportunity to speak to you about this
project today in support of the Reed
resoning application. Uh, we also
appreciate the time and effort the city
staff, council, and community members
have put in discussing this project uh
throughout the review process so far.
Um, much of my testimony on the
Highlands application applies here as
well. Uh the resoning is one step in a
broader planning process and is intended
to establish an appropriate framework
for future evaluation and uh
development. As planning advances um any
future development on the reed parcel
would still be subject to additional
studies, agency review, infrastructure
planning, engineering, utility
coordination and permitting
requirements. We value our partnership
with the city of Cheyenne and also
appreciate a thoughtful review on this
application um to which uh a pre at a
previous hearing Microsoft uh was able
to get an approval for the future land
use map amendment. U Microsoft remains
committed to working transparently with
the city staff, utility providers,
community stakeholders, and residents as
planning progresses. We look forward to
continuing those conversations as the
project moves through the city
established review processes. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mr. Downey,
>> chair and members of the committee,
Lucas Downey, community affairs with
Microsoft. For the sake of consistency
and because I don't want to test your
patience too much this afternoon, I'll
simply reiterate the same five community
first commitments that guide Microsoft's
work and communities where we operate.
We'll pay our way. We'll be responsible
stewards of the watershed. We'll create
local jobs. will contribute to the local
tax base and invest in the community
organizations and workforce development.
Those commitments have guided our work
in Cheyenne for more than 14 years and
they will continue to guide how we
invest and partner with this community
moving forward. Thank you.
>> Thank you. Any other public comment here
in the room, Mr. White?
>> Through you, Madam Chairman. Uh Michael
White. Um
I believe that um this zoning
classification
with respect to the council
I don't think it's appropriate for one
reason. Um we have antiquated laws that
reflect plan Cheyenne that was not
updated since 2014.
I think in order for the public to
understand and uh really get behind
these projects,
I think the zoning classification rules
need to be updated. U a business park
can for sure be what the people that
just talked about what Microsoft wants,
but I think we need to even go even
further to uh reclassify these and
change our rules that this project ought
to have a zoning classification of data
centers only. That's why I think this
should be defeated today. Thank you.
>> Thank you. Any other public comment here
in the room?
>> Okay, we're going to move to online
public comment.
Whoever you'd like, Jennifer. Okay, Mr.
Miller. Um, you have three minutes and
we are on item number uh 18.
>> Um, yes. Can you hear me?
>> Yes, we can.
>> Is there other online comment? Could you
possibly come back to me? Uh yes, there
is other online comment. Um so we will
go to them and come back to you.
>> Thank you
>> Mr. Nicely. We I show your hand is
raised. You have three minutes on item
number 18.
>> Yes. Uh can you hear me?
>> Yes, we can.
>> Yes. Microsoft just uh noted that they
were committed to transparency. And I'll
note that the public records request um
I believe came from Miss Madrid and
comes at an exorbitant cost because the
city um suggests that they need to pay
staff to redact the records. If we're
committed to transparency, and I assume
the city council should be, what records
need to be redacted with respect to the
issues related to the development of
data centers? Why do they need to be
redacted if we're committed to
transparency?
There's a great deal of distrust in the
city for the city council and for this
process. The city is well behind the
eightball in providing that kind of
transparency. It seems almost as if it
has had to been pushed into it. Mr.
Labour has suggested today that he would
have liked to have been invited to a
meeting today to discuss that was held
today to discuss the issues of how
development would happen especially in
South Cheyenne. I would have loved to
have been invited to that meeting and I
think probably lots of people would have
loved to have been invited to that
meeting. Why can't we have some real
transparency that's honest?
>> We are on item 18, Mr. Nicely. So, if
you can hold your comments to item 18.
I'm responding to the request of
Microsoft when they suggested that they
were interested in transparency.
Um, so I'm responding to their testimony
of the applicant.
>> Point of order. That is we're on
amendment, not their testimony. I mean,
we're on an um resolution.
>> Resolution, not on their testimony.
their testimony was relative to
the resolution and the resolution is
relative to their project.
>> So, if you can frame your comments in in
light of their res of the resolution, um
it would be appreciated.
>> We need a pause because there hasn't
been transparency. We need more
transparency
again. Um the process is we're well
behind the eightball.
Um
the distrust of the public is such that
this process needs to stop until such
time as trust can be rebuilt and the
public at large can be engaged in the
discussion.
>> Thank you Mr. Nicely.
>> Um Heather, you have your hand raised.
Uh yes. Um I just want to uh Mr. Nisley
is correct. I did submit a public
records request and was told it would
cost nearly $3,000.
>> We're on item number 18.
>> Okay. Um the current strategy with
updating the map is reactive. It allows
major industrial developers to dictate
the growth and development of this
community. It's being treated as a
simple suggestion that can be
overwritten as if it's another obstacle
for developers to bypass. Um, the odd
thing is that the city is assisting
developers in bypassing the agreement
that they made with citizens in 2014 and
the subsequent promises of a full update
that have yet to happen and are
apparently happening this morning behind
closed doors yet again. Um, apparently
the map in the future of the city is for
sale to the highest bidder. The city's
failed to update the comprehensive plan
as promised and is now using the map
being outdated as an excuse to amend
if the price is right. Because in 2014
the current data center buildout was
unforeseeable. While I do agree it was
unforeseeable that serves as a reason to
stop and think or pause not to be
confused with mortorium.
Um so the citizens have an opportunity
to participate proactively and
meaningfully in the development of that
master plan regarding sorry rather than
reactively disagreeing and begging once
the ink is already dry.
Um, certain criteria needs to be met
prior to resoning. It must align with a
comprehensive plan, which it does not,
unless this council allows the map to be
amended to suit the needs of Microsoft
instead of the community. The reszone
cannot adversely impact the environment
or properties in the area. A massive
data center campus will negatively
impact everything about the environment
and the properties in the area will
immediately decrease in their value.
Unless another big tech company wants to
build another data center, which I'm
sure they will, because you've made us a
target while other communities are
rightfully pausing to protect their
future and their citizens. The
conditions of the land need to have
changed. Currently, this property is in
the middle of nowhere. The land has not
changed just because Microsoft wants to
buy it, and Microsoft does not get to
dictate how finite resources and land
will be used for generations. Once it's
gone, it's gone forever. reszoning it to
a business park will almost certainly
lead to another data center then another
then another but at this point I'm
convinced that that's the goal of this
council anyways most of the council I
regularly speak with people who work at
data centers both construction and
operations many have signed the petition
for a pause because while they're
grateful for the opportunities and don't
want to lose them they recognize the
growing risk to our rights and our
future every time this council votes in
favor of corporations despite public
objections this has become an echo
chamber of the people who are
immediately profiting from this
buildout. From union workers to
Microsoft exe executives to the multiple
businesses associated with Cheyenne
leads. There is a balance to be found in
some of this. But at some point, despite
personal disagreements with public
voices, you need to side with the people
who hired you. The vast majority of
people in this city do not want this and
it is willful ignorance at this point.
We failed to recognize that.
>> Mr. Moody, I see your hand is raised.
Here we are on item number 18. You have
three minutes.
>> Thank you, Madam Chair. Uh, for the
record, Mark Mill City Council W three.
Just want to say I agree with what Mr.
Nicely and Miss Madrid just said.
I mean, we really do as a council need
to listen to our constituents when we're
looking at these items next Monday.
And that's all I have to say. Thank you.
>> Thank you. Okay, Mr. Miller, we're back
to you. I hope you're ready. You have
three minutes on item number 18.
>> Can you hear me?
>> Yes, we can.
>> All right.
Excuse me. Um,
Madame Chair, members of the public
services committee for the permanent
administrative record, my name is
Charles Miller and I am issuing a formal
constructive notice regarding the gross
negligence confessed lack confessed lack
of administrative bandwidth and the
resulting statutory invalidity of
advancing this business park resoning uh
and annexation. you're attempting to
process
uh the this uh
um
resoning
uh while actively operating in a
confessed state of administrative and
technical blindness. During the May 11th
city council meeting, planning director
Charles Bloom explicitly admitted that
the city is short engineers, frequently
finds itself quote unquote underwater
with the amount of work end quote and
lacks the internal quote bandwidth to
process its own industrial or its own
municipal sorry workload. Furthermore,
during the May 15th budget work session,
Director Bloom confessed on the
permanent record that his department
lacks a consolidated proactive database
for data center applications and
infrastructure impacts. Hm. I think that
kind of uh is directed towards uh Mr.
Renie considering he said that uh that
the city has the bandwidth uh to to
process these types of uh uh changes.
Um, you are blindly approving uh an
unquantifiable
uh utility burden uh without even
possessing a functional database to
track the cumulative drain on our local
power grid and municipal water supply.
Um, the administrative amnesia is
compounded compound compounded by a
confessed lack of expertise. When a
12-month moratorium was proposed simply
to allow the city to study the
environmental, electrical, and water
impacts of these hyperscale data
centers, Mayor Collins confessed on the
live microphone that the city staff
lacks the expertise to do an
environmental study and is quote unquote
not qualified to make those
determinations.
Councilman Labbourne cemented this
admission, stating verbatim to the
public that we don't have a staff that's
remotely capable of that and that
assessing these catastrophic impacts is
way beyond their capacity, quote
unquote. Yet, despite formally
confessing that you lack the engineers,
the databases, and the expertise to
evaluate these multi-billion dollar
facilities, you're actively utilizing
this bis the business park zoning
designation as a calculated scheme to
bypass the Wyoming Industrial Sighting
Act. The ISA explicitly exists
specifically to provide the rigorous
state level environmental and
socioeconomic oversight that your own
mayor and councilman just admitted. The
city is incapable incapable of
performing by jerry man jerrymandering
this BP zone. You are deliberately
shielding.
>> Thank you Mr. Miller. Your time is up.
And I believe that we have uh Cheyenne
Leeds who would like to make a public
comment.
>> Yes. Thank you Dr. Aldridge. This is
Dante Rushton, director of real estate
and property management for Shine Leads.
Shy Leads supports planning staff's
recommendation to approve the resoning.
Just to provide some background and
context, uh, business park zoning that
was adopted through the same public
process that we're seeing here today for
the reasonzoning. So, the ordinance was
adopted in the fall of 2024. So, it went
through the same processes of planning
commission, public services committee,
and city council. And so for those
questions of you know not following
process this reszone of this parcel is
following the same process to adopt the
business park zoning as it was put in
place in 2024. So again Cheyenne lead
supports the recommendation to approve
the resoning and I'll stand for any
questions.
>> Thank you. Is there any other public
comment
>> hearing none or seeing none will close
public comment. Um I would entertain a
motion.
Madame Chair, um I move to approve on
third and final reading.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion from Dr. Emmens and a
second from Dr. Renie. Is there any
discussion?
>> Hearing none. All in favor say I.
>> I.
>> Opposed.
>> This item will move forward with a
recommendation to approve at the next
meeting of the council. We are going to
take a uh break until 2:30 and then we
will reconvene to finish our agenda.
Hey, we're going to reconvene. It's 2:30
and we are getting close to the end here
in more ways than one. So, item number
30 23, please.
Number 23 of resolution overruling the
planning commission's disapproval of an
amendment to the future land use map of
plan Cheyenne, changing the land use
designation from agricultural rural and
urban residential to mixeduse employment
and amending the urban service boundary
for property generally located east of
South Gley Highway and south of the
Sweet Grass subdivision. Staff report,
please.
>> Madam Chair, members of the committee,
Conorway Planning Development
Department. Um just as a reminder with
this item uh this is basically the
resolution that overrides the planning
commission to then basically you move on
to the next item and be able to act on
that which is the actual resolution for
changing the future land use. The reason
for having this is at planning
commission uh the vote was a 3 to2 vote
which under planning commission bylaws
uh would be in approval but under state
statute you need four affirmative votes
when it comes to uh comp plan
amendments. We did not have full
planning commission that night. Um there
were two members absent so I'm unsure of
how they would have voted or what the
vote would have been with them there. uh
but with those members present it was a
3 to2 which again does not meet state
statute for approval but would have met
planning commission's bylaws for
approval. So that's what this resolution
is. It is just basically overruling um
that determination and then the next
item would be the actual future land use
map amendment. With that I am available
for any questions.
>> Thank you sir. Any questions from
committee for with the staff? Okay. Uh
Mr. Mr. Labour, I think your green light
was on first.
>> Thank you, Mr. White. So,
might we expect some resolution of this
conflict between the bylaws and statute?
>> Madam Chair, through you. So, we haven't
updated planning commission bylaws in
quite a few years. Um,
this hasn't come up all that much. Um,
it just seems to come up when we don't
have full planning commission. Um, so we
haven't really noticed it or knew about
it until it's happened. Uh, and this is
really it's come up more recently with
the amount of future land use map
amendments we've had. Uh, which we keep
hearing from the public is because our
map is from 2014 which we are planning
to uh, basically update here in the next
year with our um, once we have a
consultant on board. So that'll start
its process.
I have talked with the attorneys a
little bit on what potentially needs to
be fixed so we can have that
clarification in there. Uh we have not
moved to make any changes yet, but that
is something that we're aware of that
probably needs to be fixed when it comes
to the bylaws. Just to either reference
state statute or um make it clear that
because of state statute when it comes
to future land use map amendments, the
chair can vote because it does say a
majority of the commission. yet bylaws
don't allow the chair to vote unless
there's a tie uh which was the case at
planning commission uh with this item.
So for that staff is aware of it. Uh
again we've only talked with the
attorneys a little bit about it. So it
is something we know that probably needs
to be fixed but we have not fixed it
yet.
>> Thank you.
>> Dr. Evans, did you still have a
question?
>> Um thank you Madam Chairman. And my
question was in in line with um Mr.
having been on many many boards in the
past usually when there's not a quorum
right from the beginning you don't vote
on things so I I guess I'm a little
surprised
>> and madam chair through you uh so there
was a quorum so we still had quorum it
was just we didn't have the necessary
amount of votes required
>> to have a recommendation of approval or
approval move forward so there was a
quorum because it could have been a four
to one vote could have been Well, I
guess yeah, it could have been actually
would just been four to zero or because
the chair can't vote without the tie.
So, you would have had a 3 to one or
some some other number combination with
four members that could vote, but we did
have quorum.
>> Thank you for that clarification.
>> I do have a question. Um, how many
members do you have on the planning
commission? Everyone is present.
>> Man, you there are seven. And how many
and how many absences are they allowed
before they're asked to resign or
removed
>> mentor through you? So unexcused
absences would be three. Um in this case
for this specific meeting I was very
well aware of at least one of them. Uh
he did have a conflict. It was our
newest member. He let me know way ahead
of time. Uh his son was being getting
married in California. Feel like that's
a pretty excusable uh reason to not be
able to be
>> not if they're really committed
>> to be here.
>> Just kidding. Just kidding.
>> So, uh I would say that he had a very
excusable reason. I'm trying to remember
if I had an email from our other
planning commission member or not. Um
but generally they do let me know ahead
of time. It was just unfortunately we
didn't have full planning commission
that evening.
>> Thank you.
>> Okay. Um any other public comment on
this item?
I should say any public comment on this
item?
I see um Mr. Miller, your hand is
raised. You may go ahead. We are on item
number 23 and you have three minutes.
>> Can you hear me?
>> Yes, we can.
>> Madam chair, members of the committee,
for the permanent administrative record,
my name is Charles Miller. My testimony
is strictly gerine to item number 23,
the resolution attempting to overrule
your own planning commission's
disapproval of the Highlands future land
use map amendment and the expansion of
the urban service boundary. I'm placing
a formal constructive notice on the
record that adopting this resolution is
an indefensible violation of the Tonga
Doctrine and the Wyoming Administrative
Procedure Act. You are formally
overruling the planning experts of this
county to codify an act of corporate
supremacy. First, you cannot legally
bridge the analytical gap required to
override an expert planning denial
because you have absolutely no
substantial evidence to justify it.
Microsoft's own representative, Rachel
Irwin, formerly confessed on the public
record regarding this exact 3500 acre
expansion. Given the early stage of this
effort, Microsoft has not yet advanced
detailed design for the campus, quote
unquote. When pressed by the planning
commission on the basic engineering,
heat and water telemetry required to
justify expanding an urban service
boundaries, she explicitly admitted, I
do not have any of that information at
my disposal. You are passing a formal
resolution to override your own planning
commission for a ghost project. Under
the Tanga doctrine, overriding a
constitutional master plan without
empirical engineering data is not a
finding of fact. It is a legally
reversible declaration of faith. Second,
this resolution represents a statutory
abandonment of the general welfare of
Cheyenne. Your own planning staff
documented exactly why this map
amendment failed to secure approval.
City planner Connor White explicitly
testified on the record that this
specific map alteration, quote unquote,
would remove areas from anticipated
residential development at the time when
the city needs residential development.
It is an egregious fiduciary
contradiction for this administration to
beg the federal government and private
corporations for multi-million dollar
bailouts to build affordable housing
while you simultaneously rewrite the
master plan to destroy hundreds of acres
of prime master planned residential
acreage to accommodate a tech monopoly.
Third, amending the urban service
boundary forces the working-class
taxpayers of Cheyenne to absorb a
massive unquantifiable utility
liability. The BOPU confessed on the
live microphone that this 3500 acre
territory was completely outside of our
master plan and that no one ever
expected development to go over that
ridge. BOPU admitted that providing
water to the site will require
significant new infrastructure,
including a dedicated lift station and
three different pressure zones. You're
expanding the city's utility liability
into a completely unmapped basin for a
developer that refuses to provide a
finalized utility master plan. Finally,
you're executing this override to
facilitate a confessed corporate land
banking scheme. Microsoft's agent
explicitly admitted that the complete
buildout of the site, quote unquote,
would likely be a 10 to 20-year phase
development and stunningly confessed on
the record that they do not yet own this
property. You're expanding the city's
utility boundaries and overriding the
future land use map of Cheyenne for a
developer that does not even own the
dirt, possesses no blueprints, and plans
to hoard the land for the next two
decades. Passing this resolution
codifies an arbitrary and capricious
abuse of discretion directly into the
permanent administrative transcript. You
are overwriting the planning experts of
this county based on a corporate
hallucination. The record is closed
against you and if you adapt adopt this
resolution today, you're manufacturing
an ultravirus act. I demand a motion to
>> Thank you, Mr. Miller.
>> Okay. Is there any other public comment?
Hearing none, we'll close public
comment. I would entertain a motion.
>> Madam Chairwoman, I move to adopt.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion from Dr. Renie, a
second from Dr. Emmens. Is there any um
discussion? Yes, Dr. Emmens.
>> Um thank you, Madam Chairwoman. Um,
I don't think that we have any option
other than
to adopt this overruling because if we
don't, we are approving an illegal vote,
a decision that was made outside of the
the legal capacity. So, I'm and I was
thinking about that when Doug when Mr.
Miller was talking because I guess the
other option would be to accept an
illegal vote, which my guess is he would
probably have issues with that as well.
So, I just don't think we have any other
option other than to adopt it
considering that the uh vote violated
state statute. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Dr. O'Ne. Did you have a
comment?
Madam, yeah, Madam Chairman, I don't I
don't know where to begin. Um, but for
the permanent administrative record, I
guess I wanted to remind Mr. Miller that
our attorney has said that the Topanga
doctrine, which was a ruling in regard
to Panga Canyon in the LA area, refers
to California only and does not apply to
Wyoming. So, um I wish he would take
that up with our attorney's office
rather than keep citing it to us when
our attorney says it doesn't apply. Um,
and
I I think people have to realize this
area maybe never
maybe never would have deal certainly
wouldn't developed as residential
because with the with the required lift
stations and extra infrastructure. I
don't think it would ever would have
pencled out for a residential developer.
So, um, actually by allowing Microsoft
to
go ahead and do this, um,
it does extend the limits of the city
farther to the south, which maybe they
never would have been to. And, um,
actually, Madam Chairwoman, I'm spending
my time trying to rebut Mr. Miller, and
I'm kind of off target, so I apologize.
>> If I remember correctly, um, Dr. for any
the land owner did share that he's been
trying to sell that property for 35
years for residential and it just has
never worked. So, um any other
discussion?
All hearing none. All in favor say I.
>> I.
>> Opposed?
>> No.
>> This item will move forward with our
recommendation to approve at the next
meeting of the council item number 24.
Number 24, resolution amending the
future land use map of plan Cheyenne,
changing the land use from agricultural
rural and urban residential to mixeduse
employment and amending the urban
service boundary for property generally
located south of South, excuse me,
located east of South Kley Highway and
south of Sweetg Grass subdivision. Okay.
Staff report, please.
>> Madam Chair, members of the committee,
Counterway Planning and Development
Department. So, I just want to clarify a
couple things uh with this because this
is the future land use actual resolution
for that. Um,
we've had a couple different future land
use map amendments on the agenda
recently. There was the one for the Reed
property which was what was item 18's
resoning for. That was the one where the
land owner actually um hadn't been able
to sell it for residential.
um that also had a bunch of different
future land uses for mixed use
commercial residential variety of
things. This future land use map
amendment, this entire area is currently
under the future land use map as
agricultural rule.
That is not as Mr. Miller keeps
apparently quoting me on um being for
residential development. Um
anything that we have that's basically
agricultural rule
is way out past what our urban service
boundary is. It's most of the time what
we did not believe we would ever extend
to or develop with residential.
There's always the potential it could um
but it was mostly just meant as this
possibly just going to be agriculture um
for the foreseeable future. Now
obviously that changes that's why we
have this request. Um this does extend
the urban service boundary. Um the
reason for extending the urban service
boundary and why it should be extended
if this land gets developed they will
have to bring in utilities. So they will
have to bring water and sewer that makes
it serviceable. Um that needs to be
within the urban service boundary. Um I
think Dr. Grinny probably stated it best
when you look at this area and why staff
support this supports this is you need a
large developer somebody who can extend
those services to the area. Um, it would
probably be challenging for a
residential developer to do so in this
area. Again, from what BOPU has stated,
it is going to take a lot of
engineering, the lift station and all of
that. So,
staff does recommend approval of
basically the future land use map from
agricultural rule to mixeduse
employment. It is not for the entire
area being annexed either. Um
this is only for the area that basically
they plan to reszone to uh business
park. And I would also say I would
recommend approval because this
governing at the moment there is the
recommendation of approval for the
zoning map amendment going into third
reading which you need the future land
use map amendment to really support that
reszoning to BP. So because that does
have a recommendation of approval uh
from this committee, I would say that uh
staff would recommend that this future
land use map also be recommended for
approval uh for Monday night.
>> Thank you.
Any questions from committee for staff?
Okay. Public comment, Mr. Emmens.
Madam Chair, city council members, uh,
Brad Emmons, AVI, the one thing I would
like to point out, um, besides what
Connor had said is in the business park
zoning ordinance that this council just
passed, uh, it specifically says that
areas designated it as agricultural and
rural are to be looked at for the BP
zone. So this area already um has that
designation and so therefore um moving
it to mixed use employment or leaving it
agricultural rule would be um very
similar. So um the future land use the
zoning that BP ordinance does
contemplate that in this area as well.
Thank you.
>> Thank you. Any other public comment here
in the chambers?
Okay, we will go to online. Um, I see
your hand raised, Heather, if you would
like to comment on We are on item number
24.
>> Um, yes. I just I think it's one thing
for city council members or planning
committee members to question Mr. Miller
and, you know, one of the things he's
saying, but I find it really
inappropriate that there's a city
planner that's mocking him and laughing.
I I find that actually egregious.
Um, as far as updating the map, um, and
using the fact that the 2014 map is
outdated, I think that's I think I think
the fact that it's outdated actually
kind of serves the opposite purpose,
which is that
um,
there needs to be an updated map and I
understand that it's, you know, there's
an RFP out and it's going to take at
least a year at least, but I just don't
find it ethical to continue to amend the
map in favor of anybody honestly. I
don't like whether it's Microsoft or
my brother. I don't you know I don't I
don't find it appropriate to continuing
to amend the map um because that's
something that is supposed to be done
with a lot of public input and right now
that's not happening and I don't think a
noon public service committee meeting
counts as public input. I don't people
don't have the
the opportunity to come to these
meetings whether you know all the time
like we have we have jobs and families
and we shouldn't have to police
everything that's happening and I think
it's a shame that we find ourselves in
that position. Thank you.
>> Thank you. Okay, we have Mr. Miller um
with his hand raised. We are on item
number 24 and you have three minutes Mr.
Miller.
Can you hear me?
>> Yes, we can.
>> Um, Charles Charles Miller, for the
record, um, uh, Madame Chair through
you, I just, uh, was wondering about
Miss Emmen's, uh, statement that, uh,
she she said that she didn't have any
other choice. Um, I'm wondering is is uh
attorney Brody still on the call and and
could he maybe uh uh give the
hypothetical uh here? Uh what other
choice does she have? And then maybe
could you pause my time?
>> Uh
if you would pause Mr. Miller's time and
Dr. Emmens is going to respond.
>> Thank you, Mr. Through you, Madam
Chairman. Thank you, Mr. Miller. Uh
there are two choices. One is to accept,
one is to deny. If I accept, I am
approving a vote that was taken in
opposition to state statute.
If I deny, then in your opinion, I'm
wrong there. So those are the two
options that I saw.
>> Mr. Miller, your time is restarted.
>> Can you hear me?
>> Yes, we can. Um, I I think I'm going to
do a little bit more research in terms
of of that, but I'll address that later.
Um, uh, I must correct the legal disast
legally disastrous misinformation placed
on the record by Dr. Renie. Um,
Councilman Renie explicitly stated on
the live microphone that the Tonga
doctrine refers to California only and
does not apply to Wyoming. That is
factually and fatally false. The Wyoming
Supreme Court formally adopted the Tanga
Analytical Bridge Standard in Wilson
Advisory Committee verse board of county
commissioners 2012 Wyoming 163. Under
Wyoming law, a quasi judicial body is
legally mandated to build a genuine
analytical bridge between the raw
evidence and its final decision. You
cannot build an analytical bridge
because uh Microsoft's own agent Rachel
Irwin explicitly confessed on the
permanent record that detailed design
has not yet been developed. Overriding a
constitutional master plan in expanding
a municipal utility boundary based on
corporate bro a corporate brochure
instead of empirical engineering data is
not a finding of fact. It is a legally
reversible de declaration of faith. Um,
second, uh, uh, I'm addressing
Councilwoman Emmen's repeated claims
that the council is simply bound by
procedure, stating that advancing these
ordinances is just something that we
automatically do and just the way we do
things. Do not attempt to claim you have
no other choice but to follow the
process. Wyoming statute 151404b
explicitly strips you of that excuse.
The statute mandates that if a project
fails to affirmatively prove it complies
with the requirements to protect public
health, safety, and welfare that no
further action shall be taken. You have
a choice. You can obey state law and
halt this unengineered ghost project, or
you can choose to violate your fiduciary
duty by rubber stamping it. Do not blame
the process for your active decision to
overwrite our residential master plan.
Your own planning experts refused to
endorse this map alteration because city
planner Connor White explicitly
testified that it would remove areas
from anticipated residential development
at a time when the city needs
residential development. I also think
that uh he was being a little bit um uh
he was a little off there because on in
your own packet here it says that it's
from agricultural, rural, and urban
residential. So he he wasn't saying that
it was residential. It says it right
there. Number 24.
>> Thank you. Your time is up, Mr. Miller.
>> Madam Chair.
>> Yes, Dr. Emmens. U Madame Chair, through
you. Mr. Miller, I have absolutely no
problems people correcting me or in um
insulting me, but I don't like having
things um said
having things that I did not say
accounted to me. At no point have I said
that is just within the process. That is
just how we do things. I agree
completely with statements made by
Heather Madrid earlier that for someone
to say that's just how we do things is
not okay. I find that irreprehensible
to to make that kind of a claim. I gave
you very clearly the two options that we
had. At no point did I throw up my hands
and say it's just what we do. So in the
future, please make sure you uh quote me
correctly. Thank you.
>> Okay. Any other public comment here in
the room or online?
Seeing none, um we will close public
comment and I would entertain a motion.
>> Madam Chairman, I would move to adopt.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion to adopt by from Dr.
Emmens and a second from Dr. Renie. Any
discussion?
All in favor say I.
>> I.
>> Opposed?
>> No. This item will move forward with a
recommendation to approve at the next
meeting of the council. And our final
item on the agenda today, number 31,
resolution authorizing the mayor and the
city clerk to sign a final plat for Swan
Ranch Park 21st filing, City of
Cheyenne, Laramie County, Wyoming,
located west of Interstate 25 and north
of West Wallik Road.
>> Okay. Staff report, please.
>> Madam Chair, members of committee,
Connorway Planning and Development
Department. The plat before you actually
goes with earlier items on the agenda.
Um I believe it is the third item
basically the third item, fourth item
and fifth item. So it goes back to Swan
Ranch um rail park. This plat basically
takes the annex land, combines it with
the land to the south of it and then
also it splits a land um a property that
is already annexed that is along I25
uh into two lots. Um there is a little
bit of dedicated rightaway uh with this
plat that will then eventually have a
road that will connect and go north um
making a future kind of roadway for any
other properties that may annex over
time.
This plot was reviewed um through our
department through other various
departments um in the city um and then
recommended for approval to planning
commission. Planning Commission did
recommend approval uh of this plat and I
stand for any questions.
>> Thank you. Any questions for staff from
committee? Okay. Hearing none, we will
open it up for public comment. Is there
any public comment here in the room?
Okay. I see that we have Mr. Christensen
online. Mr. Christensen.
>> Uh Dr. Aldriz through you. This is Mark
Christensen with AVIPC. Uh, so just
wanted to make myself available for any
questions. Um, note that the larger
parcel was previously a remainder lot,
so it does need to go through the
subdivision process to be developed. Um,
this combines that portion that was
annexed. Um, dedicates some rightway for
a future Granite Peak Drive connection
and then is a simple two lot split of
that other uh lot at Quartz Drive in
Clear Creek Parkway, excuse me. Um, and
I'm available for any questions.
>> Thank you.
Okay. And Mr. Miller, I see your hand
raised. We are now on the last item on
the agenda. You have three minutes.
>> Uh, can you hear me?
>> Yes, we can.
>> Uh, Madame Chair, members of the
committee, uh, Dr. Emmens, I apologize.
Those, um, those quotes were actually
from Dr. Renie. Um, so I I apologize for
that.
>> Thank you.
Um, it gets a little bit uh tense when
I'm trying to do this uh with you guys
and and sometimes things get a little uh
>> mismatched there. Um, I did uh I did
want to uh address the uh tapanga
doctrine and with attorney Brody uh in
terms of what I had said previously
about that if if possible if he is able
to to to comment on that uh you know in
terms of how it actually does apply uh
via advisory committee verse board of
county commissioners 2020 Wyoming 163.
Um, but then uh if we could I guess wait
until I'm done, maybe he could do that.
Uh, and then um let's see here. the
Okay. So, to override a constitutional
master plan or erase residential housing
to accommodate a tech monopoly, uh uh
it's just something that we
automatically do and just the way we do
things. Uh that's what Dr. Renie had
said.
>> We're on item number 31, Mr. Miller. The
And that's Oh, that's in terms of the
Hold on. I'm sorry. I'm sorry.
>> This is with the final plan for the Swan
Ranch
>> for the Wall Road. Is that correct?
>> Uh, this is No, this is in the Swan
Ranch. It's north of West Wall Road.
>> Sorry.
the
by authorizing the mayor to sign this
final plat, you are knowingly
constructing the geographic loophole
required to bypass the Wyoming
Industrial Sighting Act. You're actively
shielding industrial developers from
state level scrutiny and illegally
stripping Larame County taxpayers of the
statemandated socioeconomic impact fees
required to mitigate the massive
infrastructure strain this development
will create. Um
the
uh
the official transcripts prove that this
administration utilize taxpayer dollars
to award a $252,522
contract directly to AVI to conduct the
Wallik road extension feasibility study.
Um
you u I'm sorry. I apologize. I got a
couple of things messed up here. I'm
just going to go ahead and uh and defer
over possibly to attorney Brody if he
could respond to uh to my previous
request. Thanks.
>> Thank you. Um just for a point of
clarification, I believe Mr. Brody can
speak for himself, but um typically the
city attorney does not give uh legal
advice to the public.
Mr. Brody.
>> Madam Chairman, John Brody, city
attorney. Um,
>> I guess Madam Chairman, I've spoken to
this. The Tanga Doctrine has never been
cited directly by the Wyoming Supreme
Court. The case that Mr. Miller cites
does not refer to the Tanga Doctrine.
The principle of administrative law that
the Tanga Doctrine stands for um is a is
a broad principle that many states
follow.
the city or excuse me the the state of
Wyoming um in Supreme Court president
has adopted that general principle years
before the Tanga case was even decided
excuse me decided
um
so yeah I'll just leave it there
>> thank you
okay
any other public comment seeing none or
hearing none I would uh close public
comment and I would entertain a motion
to adopt.
>> Second. We have a motion from Dr. Renie
and a second from Dr. Emmens. Um, any
discussion?
>> All in favor? Say I.
>> I. I.
>> I.
>> Okay. This item will move forward with a
recommendation to approve at the next
meeting of the council. We've completed
the items on our agenda today. Thank you
for your patience and cooperation. This
meeting is now adjourned.